<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | iAlja's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-26T11:31:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ialja.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alja Isaković]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goodbye Blogger, Hello Octopress!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/22/goodbye-blogger-hello-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-22T22:47:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/22/goodbye-blogger-hello-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The recent <a href="http://ialja.com/post/45336943328/hitler-finds-out-google-reader-is-shutting-down">Google Reader fiasco</a> reminded me of something I've been too lazy to take care of for too long: my blog, which I started back in 2006, was still being hosted on Google's Blogger. Now here's a question for you: how long before Google decides all blogging should be done on Google+? Ridiculous question? I don't know. I don't feel like taking chances with Google anymore. But what are the alternatives?</p>

<p><img src="/images/uploads/blogger-to-octopress.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>When WordPress feels like an overkill</h2>

<p><a href="https://wordpress.com">WordPress</a> was an obvious answer. I love WordPress. It's really powerful and it's what we use over at <a href="http://tehnik.mobitel.si">Mobitel Tehnik</a>. But is it really what my small blog, where I probably know most readers by name, needs?</p>

<p>Not to mention that "WordPress" isn't such a clear answer. You can decide to <a href="http://wordpress.org">self-host WordPress</a>, which is something I'm way too lazy to do. I don't want to deal with databases, with updates (I'm way too likely to click "Remind me later") and all that stuff.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://wordpress.com">free wordpress.com</a> blog wasn't a good answer either as I wanted to use a custom domain and have some customization options. After all, what's the point of WordPress if you can't have your own plugins?</p>

<p>That leaves paying someone else to do all the work of hosting and maintaining WordPress for me. While I fully support paying people for their trouble, I was again wondering if this little blog of mine is worth it. On bad years, I barely write more than 10 posts total! And I don't really need things like scheduling and countless categories and tags...</p>

<h2>Here come GitHub Pages and Octopress!</h2>

<p>And while I was pondering the big questions of life and my future blog hosting needs, I stumbled upon <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>, which defines itself as a "blogging framework for hackers". I don't really define myself as a hacker, but the proposition was tempting: Octopress is an easier way to set up <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>, "the blog aware static site generator powering <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a>". I started playing with GitHub Pages recently and immediately fell in love with how easy and fast is to host static HTML files there.</p>

<p>So, Octopress is free, can be hosted on GitHub Pages, is super fast because it's all static in the end, it's totally customizable, and even has plugins? Sounds good, let's give it a try!</p>

<p>Thanks to my recent <a href="/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html">Rails Girls adventures</a>, my MacBook Pro was already equipped with Ruby and Git, which made the Octopress really easy to <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">setup</a>. <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/">Deploying</a> the blog was also relatively easy with GitHub Pages, and before I knew it, I already had my new subdomain blog.ialja.com pointing to my Octopress blog.</p>

<h2>The challenges and joys of having a geeky blog</h2>

<p>I'm not saying this is something I recommend to everyone. I'm still finding my way around the command-line, as it hasn't really been part of my usual workflow until now. But that's precisely the point for me. <strong>I'm teaching myself something new</strong> and I don't ever remember having so much fun (and little frustrations) while setting up a blog!</p>

<p>The tricky part was moving my posts to Blogger from Octopress. Why did I want that, why not just start fresh? Because I wanted a relatively future proof backup that I can control. It's not just on GitHub for everyone to explore, it's also on my hard drive in nicely organized files. I even got the chance to clean up the mess that was my Blogger tags; I now use only 4 basic categories, everything else will be found with search.</p>

<p>I was surprised to find out that getting the content out from Blogger was pretty easy - hit Export and you get one big XML file. The <a href="https://gist.github.com/juniorz/1564581">import script for Octopress</a> was also easy to use once I got all the gems properly installed. Sure, the gems part got a bit tricky, but not impossible thanks to my new favorite website <a href="http://stackoverflow.com">Stack Overflow</a>.</p>

<p>And then I started playing with the import script. For that I had to pretend to speak Ruby (again, Stack Overflow plus the Ruby Documentation to the rescue). There are two main things I added to the script:
- custom permalinks for imported blog posts that mirror those on the original Blogger blog and
- information about where the blog post was originally published that I added at the end of each blog post.</p>

<p>Because I'm too lazy to go through every post to make sure it looks ok, I decided to keep the old Blogger blog alive as a reference. I don't really have any meaningful SEO to obsess about, so I decided not to worry about redirects, I'll just add a simple disclaimer about the new location on the old blog.</p>

<p>I held my breath while I committed the update with imported Blogger posts, but everything seems to be working just fine. The final piece of the puzzle was migrating Disqus comments, which couldn't be easier. Thanks to my foresight of perfectly mapping the links of old Blogger posts to new ones on Octopress, it literally took a few clicks for Disqus to take care of everything. Pure magic!</p>

<h2>A happy ending? Maybe.</h2>

<p>And so, here we are now. I am writing this blog post in Markdown in my beloved iA Writer, where all my blog drafts are made anyway. And when I'll be happy with the text, I'll fire up my Terminal, rake deploy, git commit and all that stuff, and you'll be served this page from GitHub pages. Totally geeky. And for the record, I just want to say that I love the internet and all the good folks that wrote all the wonderful open source software that made this moment possible for me.</p>

<p>If you've got any questions about the transition, let me know. Otherwise I hope you'll enjoy the new place as much as I do. I know it isn't very pretty yet. I still have to start poking around the design drawer, so I promise it will also get better looking in time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How a Lego dragon helped me explain programming in 15 minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Another <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html">Rails Girls Ljubljana workshop</a> also meant another lecture on how the internet works and the basics of programming. The goal was to ease in the participants, this time mostly high school girls, into the practical workshop that consisted of creating a <a href="http://guides.railsgirls.com/app/">web app for collecting ideas in Rails</a>.&nbsp;I was pretty happy with the <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html#more">first version of the lecture</a> I did for our very <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">first workshop</a> that used a cute story about <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>'s <a href="http://octodex.github.com/">Octocat</a>, who loves sushi, but doesn't eat fish.</p><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" /></a></div><br />However, there were two majors issues we discovered by using the first version of the lecture at the workshop:<br /><ul><li><a href="http://tryruby.org/">TryRuby.org</a>, an otherwise super cute website,&nbsp;didn't behave well during our workshop. With about 75 laptops on the same network, the site was painfully slow at moments, making it difficult for girls to keep up. Also, the order in which concepts are introduced in the tutorial is difficult for beginners (arrays make a surprisingly early appearance, for instance).</li><li>Beginners were a bit confused during the practical part of the workshop about switching from Terminal and local files with code. The meaning of all those directories and files in their Rails project wasn't very clear.</li></ul><div>All that meant I had to roll up my sleeves again and create version 2.0 that includes a giant dragon!<br /><!-- more --></div><br /><h2>Explaining the basics of programming in 15 minutes</h2>The solution to the first problem was to scratch TryRuby.org from the program. Not saying TryRuby.org isn't useful, but it's not ideal when you have a larger group of people trying to keep up with you. Instead, I advised girls to go through the exercises at home, and introduced some basic concepts of programming in a different way.<br /><br />I decided to show participants how to use <i>irb</i> (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interactive_Ruby_Shell">Interactive Ruby Shell</a>) in Terminal and how to create Ruby files in Sublime Text and running them from a Terminal (<i>ruby file.rb)</i>. In this way, I also addressed the second problem, as I gradually introduced the tools they would be using during the workshop. With different irb and .rb examples, I quickly introduced some of the most basic concepts of programming languages: different types of objects (strings, integers), methods, variables, if statements. Really basic stuff.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7T4GcLzOyrk/UTzwtRarA3I/AAAAAAAAAv4/RQujf3cOuqs/s1600/big-scary-dragon-lego.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7T4GcLzOyrk/UTzwtRarA3I/AAAAAAAAAv4/RQujf3cOuqs/s1600/big-scary-dragon-lego.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />I also decided to introduce a new metaphor for computer programs:<b> a big, scary dragon</b>, which is what code looks like to beginners. It's only upon closer inspection that you realize that the dragon is built with basic Lego blocks you get to know right at the beginning of any coding course. When learning code for the first time, you can't go straight into building a big dragon, of course; it might even seem like an impossible task! So you start practicing by making small houses, cars, until you get a hang of it or find a good coach or online tutorial that shares with you the dragon construction secrets.<br /><br />I know, the explanation wasn't perfect, and maybe it wasn't all clear to those with zero experience. I hope I was at least able to show them programming can be deconstructed into smaller, readable and easy to understand blocks.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0A5Xxw8BlxI/UTzxDuPqYgI/AAAAAAAAAwA/wdt84LDOaFc/s1600/rails-mvc-sushi.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0A5Xxw8BlxI/UTzxDuPqYgI/AAAAAAAAAwA/wdt84LDOaFc/s1600/rails-mvc-sushi.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />And finally, I also added a slide about the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/codeinmotion/mvc-demystified-essence-of-ruby-on-rails">MVC architecture</a>&nbsp;that basically serves the purpose of explaining why there are so many different folders and files in a Rails project. I heard some coaches referring to the slide during their explanations, so I think it did its trick.<br /><br /><h2>Web and programming intro slides (English and Slovenian)</h2>I wrote in more detail about how I used the rest of the slides to explain the internet and web apps in <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html">my previous post</a>, so today I'm just going to share the updated slides again. The original lecture used Slovenian slides, but I also made an English translation. If you do find any of the stuff useful, do feel free to borrow.<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661527" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/the-web-and-programming-an-introduction-simple-short-and-friendly" target="_blank" title="The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly ">The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly </a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661515" style="border: 1px solid rgb(204, 204, 204); margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"></iframe></div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/uvod-v-internet-in-programiranje-enostavno-kratko-in-prijazno" target="_blank" title="Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno">Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><br />And finally, if you happen to understand Slovenian, you can also watch a recording of my lecture below. Even without speaking a word of Slovenian you'll probably appreciate the awesomeness of the video player used below, combining both video and slides. If that's the case, you should head over to <a href="http://www.viidea.com/">Viidea's website</a>&nbsp;right away to learn more about the awesome platform that makes this possible.<br /><br /><iframe frameborder="0" height="350" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="http://tsstartup.viidea.net/rg12_isakovic_uvod_v_internet/video/1/iframe/" width="100%"></iframe><br /><br />Disclosure: Viidea was yet again one of the sponsors of <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Rails Girls Ljubljana</a> and also recorded our lectures. They are super cool, so make sure to tell all your friends about their product!<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons learned from Rails Girls and why we really do need more women in tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>It can be surprisingly easy to not notice things because "that's just the way it is". I have to admit I used to feel that way about the lack of women in tech. Just as a lot of women in the industry, I quickly started to think of myself as on of the guys and not even notice that I'm consistently a part of a minority at most tech events. In some ways, I was lucky that my mom was a geek even before that was a fashionable word and that I grew up without ever knowing computers were boys’ toys.&nbsp;But once you do start paying attention, it's impossible to turn the other way.</p><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/RailsGirlsLjubljana" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4OKqKxKxZV0/UTm6bGHM6UI/AAAAAAAAAvo/7GSUhnkdTfc/s1600/734397_517868904919059_991205745_n.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Self-driving cars will be on our roads soon, so why is it that seeing a large group of girls in front of a computer science faculty is still an exception reserved for Rails Girls events?&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table><br /><!-- more --><h2>Once you notice the gap, it stings your eyes</h2>I first started paying attention a few years ago. Ok, I'm one of the few women in tech. But surely things are changing because it's getting easier to get involved in the field? I mean, it's not like you've got to be super geeky to have a computer in 2013, programming languages have actually become readable to mere mortals, and you can learn how to code online. Yeah, all right, I see more girls popping up at events, but not nearly enough. Andraž Tori  recently did a great <a href="http://andraz.wpengine.com/2013/02/women-in-computer-science/" title="http://andraz.wpengine.com/2013/02/women-in-computer-science/">analysis of women in computer science at University in Ljubljana</a> and the data doesn't really show any positive trends.<br /><br />Which is all why I agreed to do lecture at MobileCamp Ljubljana almost exactly two years ago: <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2011/03/android-for-girls-new-frontier.html" title="/2011/03/android-for-girls-new-frontier.html">Android for girls: a new frontier</a>. I was quite self-conscious about speaking about about the topic. But you know what? It actually got a lot of positive attention! I realized that a lot of guys, developers, in fact don't usually think about half of their potential customers and they welcomed my practical tips on how to make apps more women (aka human) friendly! Crazy, right?<br /><br /><h2>Why is it even important to get more women in tech?</h2>After that experience it was easier for me to do a couple of more lectures on the topic of women in IT and especially startups. And while I was preparing the lectures (you can browse the slides below), I discovered more and more research pointing to the fact that this is a real issue in most parts of the world! <b>Women are increasingly more interested in technology, from the consumer side, but they are not as actively involved in the creation of technology. </b>Which of course means that we have tons of gadgets and apps on the market that were clearly made by white, straight guys living in a tech bubble. Nothing wrong by being a white, straight guy, mind you, but that's not even a majority group in the world. So how can we get all other groups to join the fun?<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15326515" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/what-about-the-other-half-of-your-customers" target="_blank" title="What about the other half of your customers?">What about the other half of your customers?</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15449092?startSlide=3" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/startup-women-startupday" target="_blank" title="Zakaj v startup svetu nikoli ni vrste pred ženskim straniščem?">Zakaj v startup svetu nikoli ni vrste pred ženskim straniščem?</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><br /><h2>My suspicious were confirmed by reading applications for Rails Girls </h2>One thing I found I could do was to accept the challenge of organizing <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, a programming workshop for girls. Little did I know what I was getting myself into. The demand blew our mind. Surpassed even the wildest expectations. And by reading through each and every one of the 586 applications for our first workshop, I did get further proof that this was a real issue.<br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>Girls, women of all ages are eager to learn about how the tools we use every day are made.</strong> Telling us about how their boyfriends, fathers, other men in their lives, dismiss their interest in technology with "You wouldn't understand." or "You wouldn't find that interesting." Women of all ages saying they always felt like programming was only for guys. Women embracing the opportunity to learn a technical subject in a safe environment where guys can’t accuse them of asking stupid questions. And so on and on.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-783NUjYE_fQ/UTm3TzayW-I/AAAAAAAAAu4/EyiIe92b6dQ/s640/RailsGirlsLjubljana-racunalnik-KatarinaJazbec.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Photo by Katarina Jazbec</i></td></tr></tbody></table>I already wrote about what a <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html" title="/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">magical event our first Rails Girls workshop was</a>. Not just because of the girls’ enthusiasm, but also because of our wonderful coaches. Guys and girls, experienced programmers, most without teaching experience. All eager to do it again.<br /><br /><h2>Rails Girls Ljubljana strikes again, this time with high school girls</h2>And we did it again. This time with the help of the <a href="http://www.fri.uni-lj.si/">Faculty of Computer in Information Science</a> here in Ljubljana. As we were discussing a joint workshop, we realized we could do a workshop just before high school students in our country decide where to continue their education. And so <b>we specifically tried to promote the workshop among high school girls.</b> This time we got 135 applications, though only 50 girls were under the age of 19 (I'm sure we’d get way more applications if we hadn't specified the event was mainly for high schoolers).<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.517860094919940.1073741825.466225130083437&type=3" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-r_e76USRVQg/UTm4GEmWdAI/AAAAAAAAAvE/q1aqbZm31MM/s1600/6553_517433124962637_241234575_n.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><br /></td></tr></tbody></table>We accepted all high school girls who applied. And on March 2 had another great event. It was a bit different though. Some girls were more shy, one even gave up after a mere hour - we had no such case at our first workshop, where the average age was well above 30. But some of the girls were even more eager than last time. <strong>Three interesting stories stood out for me</strong>:<br /><ul><li>A group of girls was interested in seeing the server room at the faculty.<br /></li><li>Another group was discussing about making an app for rating boys at their school. That’s, by the way, how Facebook started #justsaying<br /></li><li>A group told their coach they weren’t interested in the design tutorial. Instead, they wanted their coach to show them how to make another app, so that they would be able to do it on their own at home again.<br /></li></ul>So, you still want to tell me girls find programming and technology boring? All they need is a positive experience, and their imagination starts working at full speed! I was also pleasantly surprised when a TV crew visited our event, saying they got at least three emails&nbsp;internally&nbsp;saying they should stop by. And while we didn't make it into prime time news, we had a slot in the Saturday evening news on the national TV network. If you understand Slovenian or don't mind just looking at the action, you <a href="http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/porocila-ob-22h/ava2.160117678/00:06:31/0:8:20/">can see the news here</a>.<br /><br /><h2>Lessons learned from Rails Girls</h2>To sum it all up, here are some of the lessons I have learned while getting more actively involved in promoting technology among women:<br /><ul><li><b>We need more events like Rails Girls.</b> Seeing a room full of girls coding should be no more strange than a room full of guys coding.<br /></li><li>We still need to figure out a follow up to Rails Girls. Advanced workshops, meetups, hackatons… I don't know yet. But it needs to become a regular thing, not just an occasional flash mob.<br /></li><li>Yes, you can learn to code online in many different ways. But it's still intimidating for a lot of beginners, especially women who still think technology isn't for them. The social aspect of learning and the ability to have a coach tailor the learning experience on the spot is very important for some! <br /></li><li>Related to the previous point, a relaxed and flexible environment facilitates learning. Small groups working at their own pace, coming up with new questions as they go. All girls did learn a lot at our workshops, but they didn’t necessarily all learn the same exact things.<br /></li><li>I really enjoyed working with the faculty on our second workshop. Their coaches had no problem embracing the Rails Girls organized chaos, and they also worked well with other coaches. And I think this can be a good model of academia and the private sector joining forces. It was great seeing coaches with different background sharing their knowledge and experiences with beginners. I'd like to see that happen more regularly, and not just with coding for women.</li></ul><div><br /></div><h2>Encourage women in your life to embrace technology </h2>And by the way, it is not a coincidence that I am writing this blog post on March 8, the International Women's Day. It's a day when my Facebook feed is filled with pictures of flower bouquets and kind words of appreciation. Thanks for noticing us for one day, but you know what? <strong>If we really want to help women succeed, we need to arm them with two key things: education and technology.</strong><br /><br />ICT is continuously transforming all areas of our lives, and we can't allow half of the population to fall behind, to stay on the spectator side. Girls, women, it's time to stand up, speak up, and embrace technology! Just because you have a womb, it doesn't mean you can't handle a computer. The <a href="http://blog.fogcreek.com/girls-go-geek-again/">first software programmers were women</a>, let's not forget that! And it's not about talking over the world, it's about equal opportunities and active participation in the shaping of a better future for all of us.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://blog.fogcreek.com/girls-go-geek-again/" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CozWAob3BNM/UTm5iuTrQiI/AAAAAAAAAvY/1uftGYgX2GQ/s400/eniac+girls.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Eniac Girls started it ...&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table>Don't get me wrong, I don't want everyone becoming a programmer - I am not a programmer myself, yet I benefit immensely in everything I do by understanding how things work. There are a lot of cool things you can do with technology and soon we will have very few jobs that don't involve any digital skills. Will you be ready for that world?<br /><br />To finish on a positive note, I would like to point out that there are many wonderful initiatives around the world you can get involved in. <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, <a href="http://girlgeekdinners.com/">Geek Girl Dinners</a>, <a href="http://www.ladygeek.com/" title="http://www.ladygeek.com">Lady Geek</a>, <a href="http://sheplusplus.stanford.edu/" title="http://sheplusplus.stanford.edu">She++</a>, just to mention a few. And in Europe we have a big partnership, <a href="http://women2020.org/" title="http://women2020.org">Women2020</a>, launching today at <a href="http://www.digitaleurope.org/" title="http://www.digitaleurope.org/">DIGITALEUROPE</a>, <i>"whose mission is to promote women’s contribution to achieving the Europe 2020 vision of smart, sustainable and inclusive growth."</i> There will be many big scale events and discussions going on throughout the year, culminating in the release of Women2020 Action Plan in December.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://women2020.org/" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="56" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1aET6FgYwEc/UTm4uj_gMiI/AAAAAAAAAvM/R_kT5XvMVko/s400/cropped-women202011.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />Having just met many wonderful and enthusiastic women both from the European Comission and various big and small enterprises in <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html">Brussels</a>, I think this could be a big and important thing. But in the end, it will come to each and every one of us, women and men, to play our part and provide support for women entering the field. I certainly hope I will have a lot more to write about the subject this year. And not just about the issue, but mostly about the results of our efforts.<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I quit Evernote: why a company shouldn't choose good looks over their core functionality]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/i-quit-evernote-why-company-shouldnt.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/i-quit-evernote-why-company-shouldnt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2010/08/7-things-i-love-about-evernote.html" title="/2010/08/7-things-i-love-about-evernote.html">I used to love Evernote</a>. "Remember everything" is their headline. People talk about "outsourcing your memory" with Evernote. And I did. I made Evernote the hub for most of my work that didn't require documents. I stored everything, from meeting notes and blog post drafts to notes about our cats' health and even kept a shared notebook for our favorite recipes. <br /><p>One of the things I loved most about Evernote was its ability to keep all my notes synced across multiple devices. Sounds great, doesn't it? Yeah, except things don't "just work" anymore. </p><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-OCL2l1Vozc8/UNYA6qqypOI/AAAAAAAAAqQ/E3YhmHfJiBE/s1600/goodbye-evernote.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="215" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-OCL2l1Vozc8/UNYA6qqypOI/AAAAAAAAAqQ/E3YhmHfJiBE/s320/goodbye-evernote.png" width="320" /></a></div><br /><!-- more --><br /><h2>How Evernote started ruining meetings for me </h2><br />It's not a new problem. I first started having problems this Summer. I like to prepare for meetings in advance, so I spent some time jotting down notes in Evernote in the evening. I was a bit of a hurry to get to the meeting the next morning, so I didn't bother to press the Sync button on Evernote on my iMac. I've always had automatic syncing on, so I didn't really think twice about it.<br /><br />Except I should have. On the bus I took out my iPhone to revise the agenda for the meeting. Tough luck. The note isn't there, and neither are all the other notes I knew I created the day before, even a couple of days before! Of course, I have no way to remotely push the Evernote Sync button on my iMac, so I improvise and try to recreate the notes from memory. Luckily I hadn't yet completely outsourced my memory to Evernote despite being a Premium user, so I was able to remember most of it.<br /><br /><h2>Do elephants run Evernote support?</h2><br />The first thing I did when I got back home was to check my Evernote settings. Everything was as it should had been, automatic sync every 5 minutes. I try to manually sync, and the notes then appear on my iPhone. Ok, time to contact Evernote support. <br /><br />As a Premium user I did get a response within the business day, but I can't say it was very useful. I sent them the activity log and they recommended reinstalling Evernote. No other explanation. Was this a recurring problem? Just a faulty installation? How can I check that the next time? I suggested they implement a sync checker into the app that would actually tell the user automatic syncing has failed. I don't know about you, but I don't really have a habit of checking apps logs when I except the app to just work. In fact, I didn't even know Evernote had an Activity Log before I ran into problems.<br /><br /><h2>Evernote works fine if you're using just one device</h2><br />Back to my story. Time goes by. I replace my iMac with a MacBook Pro and spend most of the time on the same machine. Meaning, I'm mostly using Evernote on one device. I still like the idea of being able to access notes from anywhere if I need to. However, the few times I do use the Evernote mobile apps, they display weird sync behavior. I don't pay much attention to the issue as I now always have my laptop with me during meetings. So I decide to stick with Evernote for the time being and renew my subscription on December 1.<br /><br />As an Evernote user, I'm glad to see them release a big update to all their apps this Fall. The mobile one certainly has some nice tricks up its sleeve, like the sync button that's now easily accessible on the first screen (yep, that wasn't the case before). The Mac app is bloated and takes some time getting used to, but at least I can still access my notes and write them as before. Changes happen, so I don't make a big deal out of this.<br /><br />Until yesterday, when I decide to only take my iPad to work. And guess what? I want to look up something in Evernote and notice that all notes from over a week ago are missing. I press the sync button over and over again, on my iPad, on my iPhone. Nope. The notes just aren't in the cloud. And that is where my patience ends.<br /><br /><br /><h2>Are regular reinstalls the only way to make Evernote sync?</h2><br />I contact support again, specifically asking them not to serve me with an automated reply like last time. I want to talk to a human that can actually explain what's going one. But no, no such luck. Either they have machines answering the tickets or their support staff has very strict guidelines on what they can and cannot write. Meanwhile I've had very good experience with Nike Store support, you can see they are actual humans working there. You know, with emotions and the ability to write unique sentences.<br /><br />Anyhow, the official Evernote answer is that I appear to be running an old version of the app (after sending the ticket the latest update showed up in the Mac App Store) and that I should reinstall Evernote. Same reply I got last time, same instruction on how to reinstall the app (as if that was so difficult on a Mac...), yet they still haven't figured out Evernote now lives in the Mac App Store.<br /><br /><h2>Goodbye Evernote, hello alternatives!</h2><br />Dear Evernote, I just don't want to talk to support bots anymore. I don't need a bloated app that looks pretty. I want to write notes and have them in sync on all my devices. Which is why <b>I </b><strong>cancelled my Evernote Premium subscription yesterday and started looking for alternatives</strong>.<br /><br />I looked at <a href="http://springpad.com/" title="http://springpad.com/">Springpad</a> - but they have no Mac client. I looked at <a href="http://simplenoteapp.com/" title="http://simplenoteapp.com">Simplenote</a> - but apparently they've been having sync issues for a while now as well. And the more I looked, the more I started seeing <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/" title="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a> mentioned as an alternative! Dropbox? Yeah, you can easily have a folder for Notes, keep them in .txt or .rtf format and edit them practically anywhere. In TextEdit, for instance, which is one of the Apple apps I use most often on my Mac. <br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-jU0z3W5fi8U/UNYE6kSA12I/AAAAAAAAAqw/NGlEn91YDXo/s1600/springpad-simplenote-dropbox-mobile-apps.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="120" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-jU0z3W5fi8U/UNYE6kSA12I/AAAAAAAAAqw/NGlEn91YDXo/s400/springpad-simplenote-dropbox-mobile-apps.png" width="400" /></a></div><br />And as I started considering this alternative, I started discovering more and more note taking apps that can sync with Dropbox, even <a href="http://www.apple.com/icloud/" title="http://www.apple.com/icloud/">iCloud</a>. Sure, they don't have all the fancy stuff Evernote has, but I rarely use tags after I assign them, and I've only needed audio notes once in the last year. Most of my notes are text notes. I already use <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/01/im-in-love-with-pinterest-and-why-that.html">Pinterest for visual bookmarking</a>, and Springpad seems like a really nice complementary service for that. It has a great mobile app and it's very easy to have a private collection of more visually based notes and share them with my husband. For free!<br /><br />So, I realize that instead of a full blown alternative to Evernote what I really need is a bloat-free app that enables me to write, has just a few of the basic formatting options (bold, italic, the ability to make links).<br /><br /><h2>I'm in love with the simplicity of iA Writer</h2><br />And this is where I discover <a href="http://www.iawriter.com/" title="http://www.iawriter.com">iA Writer</a>. Well, discover is not really the right word here. I was aware of the app before, but I thought it was just for fancy writing stuff, a more simple version of Pages. But it turns out it now has both iCloud and Dropbox sync, a gorgeously simple native Mac app and an equally simple iOS client that works for both iPhone and iPad. The runner up was <a href="http://bywordapp.com/" title="http://bywordapp.com">Byword</a>, another simple text editor both for Macs and iOS devices. Both of these apps focus on writing text in an uncluttered way, and both support <a href="http://support.iawriter.com/help/kb/general-questions/markdown-syntax-reference-guide" title="http://support.iawriter.com/help/kb/general-questions/markdown-syntax-reference-guide">Markdown</a> for basic text formatting. And oh, they also make it easier to prepare text for the web, HTML tags and all. Bingo!<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" height="281" mozallowfullscreen="mozallowfullscreen" src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/33964031?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff" webkitallowfullscreen="webkitallowfullscreen" width="500"></iframe> <br /><a href="http://vimeo.com/33964031">iA Writer now with iCloud</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/ia">Oliver Reichenstein</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div><h2>iCloud and Dropbox to the rescue</h2><br />Yeah, I know, I'm quite biased. All the gadgets I use were designed by Apple in California (and Assembled in China, of course), so I didn't blink twice because there's no Android or Windows support in either of these apps. However! I did manage to export all my notes from Evernote to Dropbox using <a href="https://www.cloudhq.net/">cloudHQ</a> in .txt format, which means I can access and edit them anywhere. And while I'll be using iCloud in iA Writer for notes I am using the most (offline ability tipped the scale), I'll keep using Dropbox as a storage/backup tool for less frequently used notes. Spotlight will make sure I can easily find old notes in the Notes folder on my Dropbox.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iEsxNDNvWcA/UNYC-_-VbjI/AAAAAAAAAqg/rz0BvazfO44/s1600/icloud-dropbox.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="130" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iEsxNDNvWcA/UNYC-_-VbjI/AAAAAAAAAqg/rz0BvazfO44/s320/icloud-dropbox.png" width="320" /></a></div><br />Sure, the solution might not be as elegant as using Evernote for everything, but iCloud and Dropbox syncing has so far been good to me. And I can use the 40€/year I'll be saving for not using Evernote anymore on expanded iCloud storage if I need to (as a legacy MobileMe member I still have more than enough space, but expanding storage might come in handy if I start using iCloud more intensively in various apps).<br /><br /><h2>TL;DR: Evernote, make sure your core functionality works before focusing on the looks!</h2><br />And with that, dear Evernote, I am saying my official goodbyes. I have fond memories of you, we've had some good times together. But I just can't watch anymore as your apps get prettier and prettier and your core functionality lies forgotten in the dust. A quick Google search showed I'm not the only one with this problem. And I'm just not willing to reinstall your app once in a while to make sure it works properly. I'm not playing the Evernote lottery ("Will my notes be synced today?") anymore.<br /><br />Mind you, I'm not complaining about a free service here, I'm complaining about a service I pay for and it's just not working as advertised. Goodbye, Evernote. I am moving on, to more simple (and cheaper) solutions. I'll just make sure all notes were migrated properly and then I'll gladly uninstall your app from my Mac, as per your instructions, <strong>permanently</strong>.<br /><br /><i><b>Update:</b> Well, one thing Evernote support did right was to refund my account for the yearly subscription. Thanks, I guess, though I would rather have a functional product I was more than happy to pay for.&nbsp;</i><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/i-quit-evernote-why-company-shouldnt.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/i-quit-evernote-why-company-shouldnt.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Explaining the web and web programming with Octocat, sushi and fish]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>One of challenges of organizing <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Rails Girls Ljubljana</a> was coming up with short lectures that would prepare the girls, absolute beginners, to understand the basic terminology of the web and what they would be working on.</p>Sure, there are some existing presentations online about what programming is and where Rails fits in the whole story, but I thought beginners could benefit from something a bit more simple, funny and thus memorable. Which is why I borrowed <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>'s mascot <a href="http://octodex.github.com/">Octocat</a> and sent him off on a journey to find sushi without fish on the web. Wait, what?<br /><!-- more --><br />Have a look for yourself, here are the slides, both in English and Slovenian (the original I used for my lecture):<br /><br /><iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="mozallowfullscreen" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661527" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="webkitallowfullscreen" width="512"> </iframe> <br /><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/the-web-and-programming-an-introduction-simple-short-and-friendly" target="_blank" title="The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly ">The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly </a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div><br /><iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="mozallowfullscreen" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661515" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="webkitallowfullscreen" width="512"> </iframe> <br /><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/uvod-v-internet-in-programiranje-enostavno-kratko-in-prijazno" target="_blank" title="Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno">Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div><br />In case you find the slides useful, the main tip for presenting with them is: don't explain everything on the slides, focus on the story. In the first part, where I introduce the client-server model of the web, I didn't explain the technical terms too much. I compared IP addresses to phone numbers servers have and DNS servers to a phonebook. I do think it's good for beginners to be eposed to these terms, but they don't really need to know in detail what they mean.<br /><br />When talking about GET requests, I didn't explain HTTP or the format of a request. A GET request is all they need to hear, and you can mention that sometimes the server doesn't find what you're looking for in which case you get and <a href="http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/60-really-cool-and-creative-error-404-pages/">Error 404 page</a>. But if the server does find the web page, it sends it in HTML to your browser. Knowing all the steps will make it easier for people tounderstand that there are many steps involved into the process and that fast loading pages can only happen if all part of the process work as they are supposed to.<br /><br />In the second part I explained the different between a static and a dynamic web page using Octocat, who doesn't quite want the usual sushi. I explained the concept of a web app with the sushi chef living on the server, ready to tailor the content (or looks) of the web pages to each user's needs and interests, just like Facebook. And once you have a sushi chef, it's easy to explain Ruby as the language you need to learn to make the chef (the web app) do what you want.<br /><br />Simple, short, friendly and apparently memorable: one of the participants was just asking me about Octocat and sushi on Twitter, so I guess a different approach did the trick!<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" /></a></div><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
