<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Other | iAlja's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-19T00:45:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ialja.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alja Isaković]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Safer internet forum: lessons learned and observations from an outsider]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/10/18/safer-internet-forum-2013-lessons/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-18T20:14:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/10/18/safer-internet-forum-2013-lessons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago, I was invited to join the <a href="http://www.saferinternet.org/sif">Safer Internet Forum</a> as a speaker. Huh, me? I am aware of various safer internet initiatives aimed at children, but as I neither have kids nor work with kids, it's not really something I think about often. Especially because I imagine I can keep myself relatively safe online.</p>

<p>Still, they insisted I was the right candidate for their panel on youth innovation and creativity. The panel, skillfully led by <a href="https://twitter.com/olliebray">Ollie Bray</a> (his school has 3D printers!), also featured 14 year old <a href="https://twitter.com/PromptMeNina">Nina</a>, who has big plans for her privacy related apps, and Albert, a 16 years old security wizard and consultant. Both Nina and Albert really give me hope for the future of Europe. They are what the media should be talking about, not the latest Miley scandal.</p>

<p><img class="Safer Internet Forum 2013" src="/images/uploads/sif2013.jpeg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The importance of being connected</h2>

<p>The whole thing was an interesting experience due to <strong>lack of reliable and fast connectivity</strong> at the event venue (and in the city). It reminded me of two things:</p>

<p>A) For some people, this is a daily issue. We must get rural areas connected.</p>

<p>B) We need to <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/kroes/en/content/why-roaming-needs-go-reminder">remind our policy makers</a> about the benefits of a <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/connected-continent-single-telecom-market-growth-jobs">single telecom market</a> in Europe. Roaming must go. <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/10/9/4821692/t-mobile-announces-unlimited-global-data-roaming-at-no-extra-charge">T-Mobile</a> is leading the way, when will others follow?</p>

<p>As far as the forum itself is concerned, it was interesting to spend a few days outside my usual circle. Having to explain the word startup was a good reminder that the we need to talk more about what's going on in our industry.</p>

<h2>What is safe internet anyway?</h2>

<p>Some other random observations from the past few days:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Education</strong> is key, but it is still unclear how to reach adults. Kids at least have the chance of being exposed to the topic at school. <a href="http://www.saferinternet.org">Insafe</a> is doing a great job here!</li>
<li>Speaking of safe internet, there wasn't much talk about <strong>what safe means</strong>. Good and bad content are very arbitrary categories. Dangerously so when we start talking about <strong>regulation and internet filters</strong>.</li>
<li>Most of the participants seemed very fond of the idea of putting <strong>more regulations on the "industry"</strong>. What they don't seem to realize is that a lot of the widely spread services are being created by very young, understaffed, underpaid teams without a lawyer. Facebook can afford lobbyist, a young startup won't survive if we put more barriers in its way. Especially those that don't design services for kids, but kids happen to embrace them.</li>
<li>I wish there was more emphasis on the <strong>importance of coding</strong>, being able to build your own solutions to problems you're facing (<a href="https://twitter.com/lindaliukas">Linda</a> and I were playing the devil's advocates here). There were some awesome kids at the event, repeating how only kids can help kids be safer because they understand what is it like to be young. Great, but why don't you create your own privacy and safety tools, like young Nina does? Most adults around you don't really understand how the internet works, governments are too slow and broke, it's up to you to shape your future!</li>
<li>Speaking of not understanding how internet works, I was really taken aback by a teenager that was strongly proposing removing all <strong>anonymity</strong> from the internet. Teehee. And again, a dangerous view to have in terms of <strong>freedom of speech</strong>. Not just related to posting cat pictures, think more in terms of citizen reporting. Honestly, I think teenagers should embrace <strong>pseudonyms</strong>. Talk to the old folks, like myself, who grew up with IRC, if you want to know how that works, kids.</li>
<li>There is clearly too little collaboration between the safer internet community and <strong>startups</strong>. They see us, geeks, as crazy hacking anarchists, while we simply don't have the time, knowledge and experience to consider the needs of children when building new services from scratch.</li>
<li>This was the first internet related even with more <strong>women</strong> than man. Nothing wrong with that per se, but I still dreaming of more woman actively creating the future of internet rather than just being worried about how it might affect children. It's an important topic, but the best way to make a safer internet is to join the front lines.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What can we do better?</h2>

<p>Suggestion for next time: <strong>preserve the diversity of voices and interactive discussions</strong>. But embrace a hacker mentality. Have a <strong>safer internet forum hackaton</strong>. Bring in some young coders, have them come up with concrete tools. Made by kids for kids.</p>

<p>Just like we need more women in startups creating products women can relate to, we need young people solving their own problems. The companies that usually get public funding for tools and content aren't the ones that innovate and think out of the box. So why not bring kids into the equation?</p>

<p>For instance, kids concerned about "bad content" could build a browser for kids with a flagging/rating system for websites. With enough votes from trusted user, the address bar is green. For not yet rated gray, orange in between, and red for known offenders, requiring the user to explicitly click for access. It's not something I, as an adult, would build or use myself, but could be a tool that teenagers can build and control themselves.</p>

<p>But of course, for that to happen on scale, we have to start teaching kids about coding as a tool from an early age. I'm afraid that can only happen once their teacher also learn more about technology, internet culture, and open source principles. It's certainly a chicken and egg problem. Where can we start?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My grandma is now online]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/08/15/my-grandma-is-now-online/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-15T13:24:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/08/15/my-grandma-is-now-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spoke to my grandma over the phone yesterday. When I called, she was just <em>"behind the computer"</em>. I know she's been taking a computer class at her local center for senior citizens for a while now. But I never expected her to show so much determination and to keep at it. Well, yesterday I was proven wrong when I asked how she was doing and she excitedly told me all about how she now uses a PC every day.</p>

<p><img class="Super grandma" src="/images/uploads/babica.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Now, you should know that her husband, my grandpa, has been online for years now. He has three <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2009/02/my-grandpa-is-blogger-and-doesnt-even.html/">blogs</a>, posts photos on Facebook Pages like a pro, creates learning materials in PowerPoint, keeps a family tree online and what not. But up until this year, my grandma never showed much interest for all this modern technology. She'd frown when I visited and grandpa immediately took me aside, so I could troubleshoot some computer stuff or teach him a new trick. For her, my grandpa's obsession with his PC was just a silly hobby of his.</p>

<p><em>"I use the computer to write a journal every day now,"</em> was one of the first things my grandma proudly mentioned yesterday. <em>"I write what I planted in the garden, things like that. And I keep track of our expenses."</em> I was impressed. But the good part was still coming: <em>"And you know that I'm interested in herbs. Now I can just use the internet to see when something should be planted and gathered. And I also read news."</em> Wow, my grandma is online! <em>"And crosswords. I do crosswords every day. It's much easier now. Whenever there's something I don't know, I can just look it up on the internet."</em></p>

<p>I'm of course extremely happy for her for making the effort of learning something new, something out of her comfort zone. And she practically did it on her own. She applied for the classes, she's now practicing every day and finding new uses that fit in her everyday life. <em>"I do chores in the morning, make lunch. And then in the afternoon, it's my computer time,"</em> grandma went on. I could hear the excitement in her voice. The joy of discovering the access to the world's knowledge at your fingertips. <em>"It keeps my mind active, you know. I don't use the computer as much as your grandpa, I'm too busy for that. But every afternoon I do sit behind the computer and do something."</em></p>

<p>The story is just too good not to share. It shows that it's never too late to learn, to embrace new technologies. And it also reminds us how important it is to have learning opportunities for those who have been left behind for some reason or another and want to catch up. Everyone is not online yet, but my grandma now is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entering the digital playing field as one, big European team]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/06/22/entering-the-digital-playing-field-as-one-european-team-da13/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-22T16:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/06/22/entering-the-digital-playing-field-as-one-european-team-da13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The past few months have been a crazy roller coaster ride for me. A new job at a cool hardware startup that is trying to <a href="http://cubesensors.com">improve indoor living</a> (on top of my usual blogging about mobile tech, encouraging <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/news/neelies-digital-champions-and-young-advisers-help-women-learn-coding">Rails Girls</a>, running and what not), and I've just returned from the amazing Dublin, where I've attended this year's <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/digital-agenda-assembly-2013">Digital Agenda Assembly</a> as a member of the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/young-advisors">Young Advisor Expert Group</a>. As with our <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html/">previous meeting</a>, the best part of the event was meeting up with other advisors, <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/digital-champions">digital champions</a>, all the amazing people at <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/connect/">DG Connect</a>, including the unstoppable <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/kroes/index_en.htm">Neelie Kroes</a>, Vice-President of the European Commission responsible for the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/">Digital Agenda</a>, and many other wonderful people from across Europe.</p>

<p>You can get an overview of how Europe is moving towards a digital future in the <a href="http://blogs.ec.europa.eu/neelie-kroes/2013-digital-assembly/">video recording of the main #DA13 keynote speeches</a>. For a quick update, you can also take a look at the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/scoreboard/">Digital Agenda Scoreboard</a> below.</p>

<p><iframe width="" height="" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Zy8EsLl7gYQ " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>

<h2>Dear government(s), we are running out of time!</h2>

<p>While a lot of indicators are moving in the right direction, it is clear that we have a lot of gaps to fill. At the <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23da13&amp;src=hash">#da13</a>, I was missing more concrete action plans by EU member states on how exactly are we going to do that. And while Neelie Kroes and her team are doing a great job promoting the necessity of a <a href="http://commentneelie.eu/speech.php?sp=SPEECH/13/559">digital single market in Europe</a>, I was taken aback by how local government representatives still think this is something that shouldn't be rushed. "What's the hurry? Let's take it easy. One thing at a time."</p>

<p>Seriously? I tell you what the hurry is. We (Europe) are in a big danger of being left behind. While I love the different traditions and cultures in Europe, we cannot afford to stick to the traditional (aka painfully slow) ways of doing things if we want to create a competitive digital market in which new ideas and technologies will flourish.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>The public sector needs to embrace the startup mentality.</strong> Small, fast moving teams, able to create new services in weeks rather than in months or even years, being allowed to fail and to learn from mistakes. The <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/video/2013/jun/13/geeks-opened-up-government-video">Gov.uk team of awesome geeks</a> is a great example of this. So why are the others so hesitant in copying this agile and user-centric approach, which has been applauded both by experts and end-users (the citizens)? Look, there's no need to reinvent the wheel, feel free to copy and adapt the good, proven practices from across Europe. But the time to do this is now, not in a few years!</p>

<h2>Europe is full of untapped talent</h2>

<p>With only a few exceptions, influential startups like Facebook and Twitter are still being born (or moving) across the ocean, mostly in the sunny California. Yeah, they have the Silicon Valley. And we have the friendly and cheerful Irish people, the hard working Germans (to mention just a few), and a whole bunch of talented people with great ideas all over Europe. We can and should build something even greater by joining forces. <strong>"Europe is supposed to be one team,"</strong> Harri Koponen of Rovio, reminded us, while proudly wearing an Angry Birds shirt. That's the key part.</p>

<p>Right now, the advice we all give to consumer tech startups, looking to grow their user base as quickly as possible, is still: go for the US market, launch your service in English. Startups usually don't have the resources to figure out local regulations and languages of each of the European countries.</p>

<p>Mind you, I'm not saying we should just forget about our local traditions. I do think we can still retain our local character AND tear down the barriers that make absolutely no sense in the digital world. Why am I, as a Slovenian, not able to pay for most of the cool music services our there? Why can't I get apps that are only available in the UK app store? I won't be any less Slovenian by having access to great content across Europe. I'll just be a happier and richer Slovenian, more aware of other cultures.</p>

<h2>Embracing challenges as opportunities</h2>

<p>There are certainly a whole lot of challenges. But also <strong>great opportunities once we do decide to embrace Europe as one team, especially in the digital market</strong>. Let's open up the way for the very young, like the 13 years old game maker <a href="http://caseygameswebsite.blogspot.com">Jordan Casey</a>; let's encourage more women to participate on the forefront of the digital revolution; let's provide better opportunities for tradition to shine in the digital age (for instance, I've found the Irish to have great storytelling abilities and an eye for details); let's get every European online with the tools for creating a better future.</p>

<p>When you start at the bottom, it does often feel like an uphill battle against those at the top that don't want to change. But the world is changing, whether we want it or not. The questions is just whether we'll embrace change and lead the charge, or refuse to change and be left behind. From what I've seen in Dublin, there are many people in Europe who realize that. But we need to join forces and push for changes together. I am trying to play my own part in this, together with the other young advisors. We're already brainstorming about what's the key part of the Digital Agenda for Europe on which we, as a group, could have the greatest impact (suggestions welcome).</p>

<p>So I guess what I am trying to say is this: don't lose hope as an European, even when faced with people in your government who just "don't get it". We've seen protests across Europe creating big ripples. Why don't we also start a digital revolution together? One that would make Europe more agile and ready for constant change? Let's not limit ourselves to copying the big US trends, we are perfectly capable of creating our own!</p>

<p><img class="500 days of 750 words" src="/images/uploads/future-da13-quote.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[500 days of writing 750 words each day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/04/06/500-days-of-750-words-each-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T19:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/04/06/500-days-of-750-words-each-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I already <a href="/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day.html/">blogged</a> about why I write at least <a href="http://750words.com">750 words</a> each day when I reached one straight year of regular writing. Today I'm celebrating another milestone: <strong>500 days of interrupted writing</strong>. In other words: I've just added a Space Bird, the ultimate streak badge you can earn, to my collection!</p>

<p><img class="500 days of 750 words" src="/images/uploads/ialja-500days-750words.png"></p>

<p>That makes me quite happy, but also opens a couple of questions. Where to next? Should I continue writing? Try to keep increasing my streak, see how far I can take it?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I think the answer is yes. I am a better writer thanks to the site. I just wish I could now find something similar to improve proofreading abilities on my own texts, heh. I also think I'm a stronger person due to having achieved a crazy little goal like writing something, anything really for 500 straight days. And I'm not talking about writing for work. I'm talking about writing for the sake of writing. Writing through the really good and the really bad days. In sickness and health, if you wish. 750 words has seen it all.</p>

<p>Yes, the answer is definitely yes. I <em>need</em> to keep doing this.</p>

<p><img class="500 days of 750 words" src="/images/uploads/ialja-500days-stats.png"></p>

<p><em>Side note: after May 1st 750words.com will start charging a <a href="http://750words.com/patrons">monthly subscription for new members</a>. As an existing user, I'll have the privilege of getting a lifetime free account. But I've been a patron for quite a while and will keep donating as often as I can to keep the site running. If you stumble on these words after May 1st and are wondering whether to start paying after your 30 day free trial, I can assure you: it's worth having someone pressure you into writing each and every day.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I found great chocolate in Brussels and glimpsed the flame of hope]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CvxmxUrtotE/UTfG6vfWkTI/AAAAAAAAAuU/7IlC4L0NXBs/s1600/flying.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" height="200" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CvxmxUrtotE/UTfG6vfWkTI/AAAAAAAAAuU/7IlC4L0NXBs/s200/flying.jpg" width="200" /></a><br />I found myself in a bit of an awkward situation when I had to explain to my friends why I would be flying to Brussels this week. Sure, I knew the official answer. I have been selected as one of the 25 members of the "<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/transparency/regexpert/index.cfm?do=groupDetail.groupDetail&amp;groupID=2881">Young Advisors Expert Group on implementation of the Digital Agenda for Europe</a>" (yeah, I had to copy-paste that). I suppose it looks nice on my CV. And I will be visiting the capital of the <a href="http://europa.eu/index_en.htm">European Union</a> for the first time.</p>While I was looking forward to the trip, I didn't really have a clear idea on what to expect. There was some strange paperwork I had to fill in, some very formal documents sent around that say a lot and yet nothing at all at the same time. It started to look a bit better when they created a <a href="https://twitter.com/DigitalAgendaEU/young-advisers-nk">Twitter list of YAG members</a>. I admit I also felt a bit intimidated by some pretty impressive CVs from my fellow group members. What do I possibly have to offer? I don't even pay as much attention to politics as I should, because I get frustrated about the endless talking and too little meaningful action. Discussing important issues is all well and good, but if you don't follow it up with concrete actions, it's just a nice hobby suitable for lazy Summer evening on a terrace, with a glass of fine wine in your hand. I know, I know, big political decisions are hard and should not be made lightly. But hard doesn't mean impossible.<br /><br /><h2>My first YAG meeting</h2>Most doubts I had quickly disappeared once I actually met the other members of the YAG group, some members of <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/connect/index_en.htm">DG Connect</a> and (my new hero) <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/kroes/index_en.htm">Neelie Kroes</a>, Vice President of the European Commission responsible for the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/">Digital Agenda</a>. We kicked off the <a href="http://blogs.ec.europa.eu/neelie-kroes/young-advisers-2013/">meeting</a> by touching upon some common concerns, such as obstacles faced by startups, the inefficiency of our school to prepare kids for a digital future (and present), the lack of a single digital market and so on. But, also encouraged by <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/paul-andre-baran">Paul André Baran</a>, the Romanian Digital Champion, we quickly agreed that we shouldn't spend too much time complaining about things we all know to be wrong, but rather switch to proposing solutions. Of course, there's not much actual power you have as an external advisor. But we can bring a fresh perspective to the table, one not yet spoiled by the bubble of big institutions.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jordanh14/8528190147/" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="Neelie Kroes by Jordan Hatch, on Flickr"><img alt="Neelie Kroes" height="375" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8236/8528190147_bd96c60d77.jpg" width="500" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span style="font-size: xx-small;">Photo by&nbsp;<strong class="username" id="yui_3_7_3_3_1362609990145_1103" style="background-color: #fefefe; color: #222222; display: inline !important; font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; line-height: 13px; margin-top: 0px; text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jordanh14/" id="yui_3_7_3_3_1362609990145_1102" style="color: #0063dc; text-decoration: none;">Jordan Hatch</a></strong></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Diversity is key to finding innovative solutions. And I was pleasantly surprised to see how open the whole DG Connect team was to listening to what we had to say. They asked us to be frank and we embraced the opportunity wholeheartedly. What do we have to lose by speaking our minds? Nothing, but a lot to gain. I also loved the fact that they kept encouraging us, as a group, to get together and come up with practical propositions for the EU related to the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/">Digital Agenda</a>. Sure, the road to action is a long one and maybe even covered with wild plants, but it's good to know it exists.<br /><!-- more --><br /><h2>We can't afford to wait for the big guys to save the world</h2>But perhaps an even more important lesson of the day was learning about all the wonderful initiatives across Europe all of us YAGs are involved in. The <a href="http://b4rn.org.uk/" title="http://b4rn.org.uk/">B4RN</a> network from Lancashire (UK), who teaches anyone interested, especially women, how to fuse fiber optics and thus deliver fast broadband to rural, commercially uninteresting, areas. DIY for the digital age, "easier than knitting," says Chris Condor, one of the founders, who is acting as an observer to our little merry band and has more youthful spirit than some people a third her age. And she carries fiber optic cables in her purse, how awesome is that?<br /><br />Then there's <a href="http://www.zendigital.be" title="http://www.zendigital.be">Zen Digital Europe</a>, originally from Brussels, which promotes STEM (science, technology, engineering and math) among young girls. YAG member Mercedes, who was involved with this initiative and many others, is also wonderfully passionate about bringing more women in IT. Then <a href="http://www.telerik.com/" title="http://www.telerik.com/">Telerik</a> in Bulgaria, an internationally successful enterprise software company, which established their own <a href="http://academy.telerik.com/" title="http://academy.telerik.com/">academy</a> to provide practical IT training for people with little or no programming background - not surprisingly, it turns out such an initiative can also be great recruiting tool. All sorts of innovative competitions for schools in Lithuania. And the list goes on. <i>(Side note: the more I look around, the more wonderful women I see having a big impact in their local communities. We just need to learn to speak up more loudly and often!)</i><br /><br />All those initiatives are just the tip of the iceberg. But it gives me hope. The more we share ideas like this, the more we can achieve, bottom-up, without any big funding that drowns in bureaucracy. In that sense, the meeting was a great platform for exchanging good practices. And there's of course another important group, the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/digital-champions">Digital Champions</a>, that are playing for the same team. <br /><br /><h2>My own catalyst for action</h2>Come to think of it, I might never have gotten involved with <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, the super fun and engaging web programming workshop for women that I have organized twice now in <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Ljubljana</a>, if it weren't for <a href="http://lindaliukas.fi/">Linda Liukas</a>, the co-founder of the initiative and <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/linda-liukas">Digital Champion of Finland</a>. She encouraged <a href="http://www.alesspetic.si/">Aleš Špetič</a>, our own&nbsp;<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/ales-spetic">Digital Champion</a>, to bring Rails Girls to Slovenia, and he in turn challenged me to get involved. I am not sure if I would have had the guts to do it on my own otherwise. I had almost no experience with organizing events, but when faced with a direct challenge that could help solve an issue that was already bugging me, saying no wasn't an option.<br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Ev0CQgf8CTM/UTfJIz4CzhI/AAAAAAAAAug/YUZvgbG__jo/s1600/Screen+Shot+2013-03-06+at+23.54.12.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="286" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Ev0CQgf8CTM/UTfJIz4CzhI/AAAAAAAAAug/YUZvgbG__jo/s400/Screen+Shot+2013-03-06+at+23.54.12.png" width="400" /></a></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>As it turns out, organizing Rails Girls was probably the most meaningful thing I've done so far, with the support of various individuals and companies, of course. My husband tells me I switch to my excited voice when I talk about Rails Girls. But I needed a little nudge and I can now tell you first hand it's not as scary as it seems from the other side, especially if you have a supportive environment - and that's another thing you can't really know unless you try. I am just blown away by the support for Rails Girls from coaches, the girls themselves, the <a href="http://www.fri.uni-lj.si/en">Faculty of Computer and Information Science in Ljubljana</a>, the startups involved in the <a href="http://www.silicongardens.si/">Silicon Gardens</a> community. Actually, our only weakness is sponsorship money.<br /><br /><h2>Rolling up my sleeves even more</h2><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L57ELyE9WDE/UTfG6iD5S7I/AAAAAAAAAuA/LZaeIsqJdT4/s1600/chocolate.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" height="200" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L57ELyE9WDE/UTfG6iD5S7I/AAAAAAAAAuA/LZaeIsqJdT4/s200/chocolate.jpg" width="200" /></a>So, while I am still not entirely sure what being a young EC expert means, I am already seeing a lot of value in sharing ideas with a diverse group of people from all over Europe. And I will try my best to play my part in the sharing network. Take the experience I had in Brussels back with me to Ljubljana, borrow best practices from other EU countries, try to export the best practices we create here. Our YAG  ("yag" apparently means fire in Gypsy language) group has already come up with some interesting ideas in the Facebook group we created right after our first meeting and I think we're all excited about meeting again, in one way or another. My wish is that the next meeting will also involve whiteboards, colorful sticky notes and, ultimately, concrete proposals for action. And great Belgium chocolate, of course.<br /><br />We might not be super heroes, but I am thinking we might just be still young and eager enough to come up with crazy ideas nobody told us were impossible. I also don't pretend we're the only eligible candidates to represent our countries. I <em>know</em> there are many other people under the age of 35 around Europe with great ideas, and I'm also hoping to meet you guys and gals (if you happen to stumble upon this blog post, give me a shout!). Being a member of YAG certainly looks nice on my CV, but I also see it as a responsibility towards all the hard working and creative young people from Slovenia and other EU countries that weren't at the table with us (yet).<br /><br /><h2>What can one person do? A lot, with the right village</h2>I've seen how girls' eyes light up when they create their first web app, I've seen how excited coaches are to be sharing their knowledge at <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">our Rails Girls workshops</a>. All completely voluntarily. That is tangible change. And maybe, just maybe, if we all join our forces, we can create even more positive change in our local communities. I know the political and economical situation is anything but rosy in most part of Europe, which is definitely also true for our little paradise below the Alps. Yeah, it sucks to be young and looking for employment in quickly disappearing fields. It's going to suck for quite a while, I'm afraid. And to be honest, I don't have much hope that our politicians have what it takes to make everything good again (even though we recently got our first female PM), I'll be really happy if I'm proven wrong, but while we wait, it's even more important to get involved when you see opportunity for change. Even if it seems like just a little one, like teaching a couple of girls to code.<br /><br />It's not easy giving a big piece of yourself to a cause, more often than not for free, that's for sure. <b>But on my trip to Brussels I learned that I am not alone. And that there are some cool people with actual power that are willing to listen if we make enough positively oriented noise downstairs.</b> Let's get a party started then, not just by walking the streets, but by finding solutions, creating our own little pilots that can be scaled across the continent.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TYBfg-db8ho/UTfJUI9GeQI/AAAAAAAAAuo/rhN6HLtomio/s1600/IMG_6308.JPG" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="300" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TYBfg-db8ho/UTfJUI9GeQI/AAAAAAAAAuo/rhN6HLtomio/s400/IMG_6308.JPG" width="400" /></a></div><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
