<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Other | iAlja's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-06T19:57:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ialja.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alja Isaković]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[500 days of writing 750 words each day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/04/06/500-days-of-750-words-each-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-06T19:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/04/06/500-days-of-750-words-each-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I already <a href="/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day.html/">blogged</a> about why I write at least 750 words each day when I reached one straight year of regular writing. Today I'm celebrating another milestone: <strong>500 days of interrupted writing</strong>. In other words: I've just added a Space Bird, the ultimate streak badge you can earn, to my collection!</p>

<p><img class="500 days of 750 words" src="/images/uploads/ialja-500days-750words.png"></p>

<p>That makes me quite happy, but also opens a couple of questions. Where to next? Should I continue writing? Try to keep increasing my streak, see how far I can take it?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I think the answer is yes. I am a better writer thanks to the site. I just wish I could now find something similar to improve proofreading abilities on my own texts, heh. I also think I'm a stronger person due to having achieved a crazy little goal like writing something, anything really for 500 straight days. And I'm not talking about writing for work. I'm talking about writing for the sake of writing. Writing through the really good and the really bad days. In sickness and health, if you wish. 750 words has seen it all.</p>

<p>Yes, the answer is definitely yes. I <em>need</em> to keep doing this.</p>

<p><img class="500 days of 750 words" src="/images/uploads/ialja-500days-stats.png"></p>

<p><em>Side note: after May 1st 750words.com will start charging a <a href="http://750words.com/patrons">monthly subscription for new members</a>. As an existing user, I'll have the privilege of getting a lifetime free account. But I've been a patron for quite a while and will keep donating as often as I can to keep the site running. If you stumble on these words after May 1st and are wondering whether to start paying after your 30 day free trial, I can assure you: it's worth having someone pressure you into writing each and every day.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I found great chocolate in Brussels and glimpsed the flame of hope]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CvxmxUrtotE/UTfG6vfWkTI/AAAAAAAAAuU/7IlC4L0NXBs/s1600/flying.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" height="200" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CvxmxUrtotE/UTfG6vfWkTI/AAAAAAAAAuU/7IlC4L0NXBs/s200/flying.jpg" width="200" /></a><br />I found myself in a bit of an awkward situation when I had to explain to my friends why I would be flying to Brussels this week. Sure, I knew the official answer. I have been selected as one of the 25 members of the "<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/transparency/regexpert/index.cfm?do=groupDetail.groupDetail&amp;groupID=2881">Young Advisors Expert Group on implementation of the Digital Agenda for Europe</a>" (yeah, I had to copy-paste that). I suppose it looks nice on my CV. And I will be visiting the capital of the <a href="http://europa.eu/index_en.htm">European Union</a> for the first time.</p>While I was looking forward to the trip, I didn't really have a clear idea on what to expect. There was some strange paperwork I had to fill in, some very formal documents sent around that say a lot and yet nothing at all at the same time. It started to look a bit better when they created a <a href="https://twitter.com/DigitalAgendaEU/young-advisers-nk">Twitter list of YAG members</a>. I admit I also felt a bit intimidated by some pretty impressive CVs from my fellow group members. What do I possibly have to offer? I don't even pay as much attention to politics as I should, because I get frustrated about the endless talking and too little meaningful action. Discussing important issues is all well and good, but if you don't follow it up with concrete actions, it's just a nice hobby suitable for lazy Summer evening on a terrace, with a glass of fine wine in your hand. I know, I know, big political decisions are hard and should not be made lightly. But hard doesn't mean impossible.<br /><br /><h2>My first YAG meeting</h2>Most doubts I had quickly disappeared once I actually met the other members of the YAG group, some members of <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/connect/index_en.htm">DG Connect</a> and (my new hero) <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/kroes/index_en.htm">Neelie Kroes</a>, Vice President of the European Commission responsible for the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/">Digital Agenda</a>. We kicked off the <a href="http://blogs.ec.europa.eu/neelie-kroes/young-advisers-2013/">meeting</a> by touching upon some common concerns, such as obstacles faced by startups, the inefficiency of our school to prepare kids for a digital future (and present), the lack of a single digital market and so on. But, also encouraged by <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/paul-andre-baran">Paul André Baran</a>, the Romanian Digital Champion, we quickly agreed that we shouldn't spend too much time complaining about things we all know to be wrong, but rather switch to proposing solutions. Of course, there's not much actual power you have as an external advisor. But we can bring a fresh perspective to the table, one not yet spoiled by the bubble of big institutions.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jordanh14/8528190147/" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="Neelie Kroes by Jordan Hatch, on Flickr"><img alt="Neelie Kroes" height="375" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8236/8528190147_bd96c60d77.jpg" width="500" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span style="font-size: xx-small;">Photo by&nbsp;<strong class="username" id="yui_3_7_3_3_1362609990145_1103" style="background-color: #fefefe; color: #222222; display: inline !important; font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; line-height: 13px; margin-top: 0px; text-align: left;"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jordanh14/" id="yui_3_7_3_3_1362609990145_1102" style="color: #0063dc; text-decoration: none;">Jordan Hatch</a></strong></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Diversity is key to finding innovative solutions. And I was pleasantly surprised to see how open the whole DG Connect team was to listening to what we had to say. They asked us to be frank and we embraced the opportunity wholeheartedly. What do we have to lose by speaking our minds? Nothing, but a lot to gain. I also loved the fact that they kept encouraging us, as a group, to get together and come up with practical propositions for the EU related to the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/">Digital Agenda</a>. Sure, the road to action is a long one and maybe even covered with wild plants, but it's good to know it exists.<br /><!-- more --><br /><h2>We can't afford to wait for the big guys to save the world</h2>But perhaps an even more important lesson of the day was learning about all the wonderful initiatives across Europe all of us YAGs are involved in. The <a href="http://b4rn.org.uk/" title="http://b4rn.org.uk/">B4RN</a> network from Lancashire (UK), who teaches anyone interested, especially women, how to fuse fiber optics and thus deliver fast broadband to rural, commercially uninteresting, areas. DIY for the digital age, "easier than knitting," says Chris Condor, one of the founders, who is acting as an observer to our little merry band and has more youthful spirit than some people a third her age. And she carries fiber optic cables in her purse, how awesome is that?<br /><br />Then there's <a href="http://www.zendigital.be" title="http://www.zendigital.be">Zen Digital Europe</a>, originally from Brussels, which promotes STEM (science, technology, engineering and math) among young girls. YAG member Mercedes, who was involved with this initiative and many others, is also wonderfully passionate about bringing more women in IT. Then <a href="http://www.telerik.com/" title="http://www.telerik.com/">Telerik</a> in Bulgaria, an internationally successful enterprise software company, which established their own <a href="http://academy.telerik.com/" title="http://academy.telerik.com/">academy</a> to provide practical IT training for people with little or no programming background - not surprisingly, it turns out such an initiative can also be great recruiting tool. All sorts of innovative competitions for schools in Lithuania. And the list goes on. <i>(Side note: the more I look around, the more wonderful women I see having a big impact in their local communities. We just need to learn to speak up more loudly and often!)</i><br /><br />All those initiatives are just the tip of the iceberg. But it gives me hope. The more we share ideas like this, the more we can achieve, bottom-up, without any big funding that drowns in bureaucracy. In that sense, the meeting was a great platform for exchanging good practices. And there's of course another important group, the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/digital-champions">Digital Champions</a>, that are playing for the same team. <br /><br /><h2>My own catalyst for action</h2>Come to think of it, I might never have gotten involved with <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, the super fun and engaging web programming workshop for women that I have organized twice now in <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Ljubljana</a>, if it weren't for <a href="http://lindaliukas.fi/">Linda Liukas</a>, the co-founder of the initiative and <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/linda-liukas">Digital Champion of Finland</a>. She encouraged <a href="http://www.alesspetic.si/">Aleš Špetič</a>, our own&nbsp;<a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/ales-spetic">Digital Champion</a>, to bring Rails Girls to Slovenia, and he in turn challenged me to get involved. I am not sure if I would have had the guts to do it on my own otherwise. I had almost no experience with organizing events, but when faced with a direct challenge that could help solve an issue that was already bugging me, saying no wasn't an option.<br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Ev0CQgf8CTM/UTfJIz4CzhI/AAAAAAAAAug/YUZvgbG__jo/s1600/Screen+Shot+2013-03-06+at+23.54.12.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="286" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Ev0CQgf8CTM/UTfJIz4CzhI/AAAAAAAAAug/YUZvgbG__jo/s400/Screen+Shot+2013-03-06+at+23.54.12.png" width="400" /></a></div><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><br /></div>As it turns out, organizing Rails Girls was probably the most meaningful thing I've done so far, with the support of various individuals and companies, of course. My husband tells me I switch to my excited voice when I talk about Rails Girls. But I needed a little nudge and I can now tell you first hand it's not as scary as it seems from the other side, especially if you have a supportive environment - and that's another thing you can't really know unless you try. I am just blown away by the support for Rails Girls from coaches, the girls themselves, the <a href="http://www.fri.uni-lj.si/en">Faculty of Computer and Information Science in Ljubljana</a>, the startups involved in the <a href="http://www.silicongardens.si/">Silicon Gardens</a> community. Actually, our only weakness is sponsorship money.<br /><br /><h2>Rolling up my sleeves even more</h2><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L57ELyE9WDE/UTfG6iD5S7I/AAAAAAAAAuA/LZaeIsqJdT4/s1600/chocolate.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" height="200" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-L57ELyE9WDE/UTfG6iD5S7I/AAAAAAAAAuA/LZaeIsqJdT4/s200/chocolate.jpg" width="200" /></a>So, while I am still not entirely sure what being a young EC expert means, I am already seeing a lot of value in sharing ideas with a diverse group of people from all over Europe. And I will try my best to play my part in the sharing network. Take the experience I had in Brussels back with me to Ljubljana, borrow best practices from other EU countries, try to export the best practices we create here. Our YAG  ("yag" apparently means fire in Gypsy language) group has already come up with some interesting ideas in the Facebook group we created right after our first meeting and I think we're all excited about meeting again, in one way or another. My wish is that the next meeting will also involve whiteboards, colorful sticky notes and, ultimately, concrete proposals for action. And great Belgium chocolate, of course.<br /><br />We might not be super heroes, but I am thinking we might just be still young and eager enough to come up with crazy ideas nobody told us were impossible. I also don't pretend we're the only eligible candidates to represent our countries. I <em>know</em> there are many other people under the age of 35 around Europe with great ideas, and I'm also hoping to meet you guys and gals (if you happen to stumble upon this blog post, give me a shout!). Being a member of YAG certainly looks nice on my CV, but I also see it as a responsibility towards all the hard working and creative young people from Slovenia and other EU countries that weren't at the table with us (yet).<br /><br /><h2>What can one person do? A lot, with the right village</h2>I've seen how girls' eyes light up when they create their first web app, I've seen how excited coaches are to be sharing their knowledge at <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">our Rails Girls workshops</a>. All completely voluntarily. That is tangible change. And maybe, just maybe, if we all join our forces, we can create even more positive change in our local communities. I know the political and economical situation is anything but rosy in most part of Europe, which is definitely also true for our little paradise below the Alps. Yeah, it sucks to be young and looking for employment in quickly disappearing fields. It's going to suck for quite a while, I'm afraid. And to be honest, I don't have much hope that our politicians have what it takes to make everything good again (even though we recently got our first female PM), I'll be really happy if I'm proven wrong, but while we wait, it's even more important to get involved when you see opportunity for change. Even if it seems like just a little one, like teaching a couple of girls to code.<br /><br />It's not easy giving a big piece of yourself to a cause, more often than not for free, that's for sure. <b>But on my trip to Brussels I learned that I am not alone. And that there are some cool people with actual power that are willing to listen if we make enough positively oriented noise downstairs.</b> Let's get a party started then, not just by walking the streets, but by finding solutions, creating our own little pilots that can be scaled across the continent.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TYBfg-db8ho/UTfJUI9GeQI/AAAAAAAAAuo/rhN6HLtomio/s1600/IMG_6308.JPG" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="300" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TYBfg-db8ho/UTfJUI9GeQI/AAAAAAAAAuo/rhN6HLtomio/s400/IMG_6308.JPG" width="400" /></a></div><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I write at least 750 words a day]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day.html"/>
    <updated>2012-11-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-j3TUtDyCL8A/ULClgqP_WRI/AAAAAAAAAnY/1nZW8lnc-MI/s1600/badge.pegasus.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-j3TUtDyCL8A/ULClgqP_WRI/AAAAAAAAAnY/1nZW8lnc-MI/s1600/badge.pegasus.png" /></a><p>One year ago I first came across this strange website, <a href="http://750words.com/"><b>750words.com</b></a> (thanks, <a href="http://swizec.com/blog/750-words-a-day-keeps-the-insanity-away/swizec/1703">Swizec</a>!). Simple concept, simple instructions. Write 750 words. And come back again tomorrow, write at least 750 more. Rinse and repeat. 750 words. Each and every day in the past year. Now a total of 356,548 words, 367 days.</p><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-8VLtGvzcrxY/ULCkYKFYDlI/AAAAAAAAAm0/xPGrElhDOJI/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.55.48.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-8VLtGvzcrxY/ULCkYKFYDlI/AAAAAAAAAm0/xPGrElhDOJI/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.55.48.png" /></a></div><!-- more --><br />Celebrating the one year anniversary of my 750 words habit makes me look back at the year that is now coming to an end. It certainly has been an interesting one. The health part of the equation wasn't all that good for me, especially due to annoying <a href="http://runjourney.tumblr.com/post/34045812473/have-i-given-up-on-my-running-journey">running injuries</a> I'm still recovering from. Yet on the other side of the equation I got some really great new work opportunities and challenges that make it easier to get out of bed in the morning. Twice a week now I even make myself jump out of bed, feed the cats, get dressed in my running gear, and finish my morning run before 8 AM, so I have the rest of the day "free". Free meaning being able to work without distractions.<br /><br />On those excitingly busy days my morning ritual also involves writing at least 750 words a day. In sickness, in health. Whether I feel inspired and write really great stuff, sometimes even a thousand words at a time, or whether I feel completely empty headed and just go with the flow. Often I can't think of anything smart to say and I just write about my day. Journal mode, I call it. But even by doing that I often uncover the unexpected.&nbsp;When you can't stop before reaching 750 words, you have to dig deeper into yourself and often stumble upon buried treasure or skeletons.<br /><br />I guess that's one of the things I like most about the 750 words challenge. When I start writing, I rarely know how the story is going to end. Sometimes the trail I follow is a straight line, but more often than not the trail takes scenic detours into strange lands. Another interesting thing is the fact that the website provides stats about the style and content of your writing. It shows your mood, your attitude towards the world. For instance, my level of Happy is above the world average, especially in recent times. I also seem less focused on the past than others, more on the present.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1yk7I4YEK_c/ULCeo8CEVhI/AAAAAAAAAl0/0j4gUmasBPE/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.56.09.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="196" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1yk7I4YEK_c/ULCeo8CEVhI/AAAAAAAAAl0/0j4gUmasBPE/s400/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.56.09.png" width="400" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span style="color: #cccccc; font-size: x-small;">I seem to be having plenty of "Happy" recently!</span></i></td></tr></tbody></table><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--BjB5WVhs-Y/ULCepOcgc5I/AAAAAAAAAmA/rnUXeJlTSE0/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.57.07.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/--BjB5WVhs-Y/ULCepOcgc5I/AAAAAAAAAmA/rnUXeJlTSE0/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.57.07.png" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span style="color: #cccccc; font-size: x-small;">Living in the present, recently writing about the future</span></i></td></tr></tbody></table><br />Writing at least 750 words every day, just for the sake of it, has also made me a better writer. Most of what I do for a living involves writing, so that's a pretty big deal to me. But I never use my 750 words for job related writing. No, the time spent on the website is my time for practice.&nbsp;Writing without a specific goal in mind about anything in the world can do wonders.&nbsp;I no longer put off the most annoying phase of writing - the beginning. I can now sit down, start jotting down thoughts until it all starts coming together. You can always edit stuff later. The important thing is to start.<br /><br />I have to admit that when I was just starting out, the badges for different achievements were a great motivational tool. Sure, I was still happy to become one of the 239 people with a Pegasus badge for 365 consecutive days of writing. But it's not really about that anymore. My now 367 days long streak of writing is a living proof of my determination, of my strength. It might not sound like much, but making time (at least 11 minutes) for writing every single day is not always easy. The key part being <i>every single day</i>. I wrote while being sick in bed, barely able to keep my eyes open. I wrote on insanely busy days or insanely great days when I'd rather not sit behind the computer. In the sun, in the rain, during storms, I wrote. And the result of that really can't be measured in badges. It's just priceless.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-OmqjRNPYvWk/ULCenlw0B4I/AAAAAAAAAlo/o6wyQfpezyo/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.55.11.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-OmqjRNPYvWk/ULCenlw0B4I/AAAAAAAAAlo/o6wyQfpezyo/s1600/Screen+Shot+2012-11-24+at+10.55.11.png" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span style="color: #cccccc;">750words.com badges I have earned many, but that's not really the point anymore</span></i></td></tr></tbody></table><br />And while writing every day isn't for everyone, I would encourage everyone to try doing something like this for a year. Whether it's taking 10 minutes in the morning or evening for meditation. Or 10 minutes for making and drinking tea. Whatever you like. Pick one thing and try to make a new habit out of it. It will end up making you a better, stronger person, in one way or another. And even if you fail along the way, break your streak, don't give up. You can always start again.<br /><br />Thank you, 750words, thank you for making me a better writer and a better person! And don't worry, this isn't a goodbye, this is just a toast. After all, there's this 500 days badge (Space Bird!) still waiting to be conquered. Now that's just 133 days away. Nothing compared to the 367 I already completed. Although, to be completely honest, it doesn't really get that much easier. Every day is still a struggle on its own, but with every day I add to the streak, it seems more foolish to just give up. Who knows, maybe I can even reach a 750 days streak of 750 words? There's no badge for that (yet), but that would still be a pretty sweet achievement.<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/11/why-i-write-at-least-750-words-day.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharable Bits: Compliments, Doing Nothing, Standing Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2011/01/sharable-bits-compliments-doing-nothing.html"/>
    <updated>2011-01-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2011/01/sharable-bits-compliments-doing-nothing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;">Blog post: Genuine compliments matter</span></b><br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://coolcatteacher.blogspot.com/2011/01/students-say-id-rather-have-compliment.html"><b>Students say: "I'd rather have a compliment than sex or pizza!"</b></a></div><br /><b>Why it's worth sharing:</b> Vicki A. Davis reminds us about how important it is to give genuine compliments to our students and colleagues every day. I certainly try to follow this advice in my day to day work. Remembering to thank people for their effort and acknowledging their success is a simple gesture that can make a big impact. After all, we all want to be good at what we're doing and to know that what we do is meaningful, don't we?<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;">Challenge: Do Nothing for Two Minutes</span></b><br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.donothingfor2minutes.com/"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2DSTcHBBvTM/TT2CuUTc9JI/AAAAAAAAAqs/XKTRdWJDWRI/s1600/do-nothing-for-2-minutes.png" /></a></div><br /><b>Why it's worth sharing:</b>&nbsp;It's a <a href="http://www.donothingfor2minutes.com/">simple website</a> with a simple idea: relax and do nothing for only two minutes. Easy, no? Well, it turns out it can be quite a challenge if you're used to constantly check your e-mails, Facebook, Twitter and what not. It's certainly a nice idea that encourages to stop and relax, even if it is just for our couple of minutes. Perhaps we'd all felt a little bit better if we passed this simple challenge every day. (via <a href="http://mashable.com/2011/01/22/do-nothing-website/">@mashable</a>)<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;">Idea: Standing desk</span></b><br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ginatrapani/5357711375/" title="Standing desk by ginatrapani, on Flickr"><img alt="Standing desk" height="400" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5082/5357711375_3850019910.jpg" width="300" /></a></div><br /><b>Why it's worth sharing:</b> Gina Trapani's blog post <a href="http://smarterware.org/7102/how-and-why-i-switched-to-a-standing-desk">Why and How I Switched to a Standing Desk</a> provides a nice overview of the transition from a traditional "sitdown desk" to a standing desk and working on your feet. As someone, who tends to sit behind the computer desk in awkward positions all day long, I find this idea quite intriguing. I admit - I haven't decided to make the switch yet, but at least the post reminded me that I should get up and stretch more often during the day.<br /><br /><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #999999;"><b>Sharable Bits</b> is a series of weekly posts that will highlight some of the most interesting bits and bytes that I stumble upon. No bad news, just ideas that inspire, touch or entertain in a unique way.</span></i><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2011/01/sharable-bits-compliments-doing-nothing.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2011/01/sharable-bits-compliments-doing-nothing.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Holidays]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2010/12/happy-holidays.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2010/12/happy-holidays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I just wanted to stop by for a minute to wish everyone <b>Happy Holidays and a 2011 full of new discoveries</b> with my favorite video of this holiday season. See you next year!<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><object height="340" width="560"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/nn2h3_aH3vo?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US"></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"></param><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"></param><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/nn2h3_aH3vo?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="560" height="340"></embed></object></div><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2010/12/happy-holidays.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2010/12/happy-holidays.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
