<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Education | iAlja's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-23T10:01:28+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ialja.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alja Isaković]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How a Lego dragon helped me explain programming in 15 minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Another <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html">Rails Girls Ljubljana workshop</a> also meant another lecture on how the internet works and the basics of programming. The goal was to ease in the participants, this time mostly high school girls, into the practical workshop that consisted of creating a <a href="http://guides.railsgirls.com/app/">web app for collecting ideas in Rails</a>.&nbsp;I was pretty happy with the <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html#more">first version of the lecture</a> I did for our very <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">first workshop</a> that used a cute story about <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>'s <a href="http://octodex.github.com/">Octocat</a>, who loves sushi, but doesn't eat fish.</p><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" /></a></div><br />However, there were two majors issues we discovered by using the first version of the lecture at the workshop:<br /><ul><li><a href="http://tryruby.org/">TryRuby.org</a>, an otherwise super cute website,&nbsp;didn't behave well during our workshop. With about 75 laptops on the same network, the site was painfully slow at moments, making it difficult for girls to keep up. Also, the order in which concepts are introduced in the tutorial is difficult for beginners (arrays make a surprisingly early appearance, for instance).</li><li>Beginners were a bit confused during the practical part of the workshop about switching from Terminal and local files with code. The meaning of all those directories and files in their Rails project wasn't very clear.</li></ul><div>All that meant I had to roll up my sleeves again and create version 2.0 that includes a giant dragon!<br /><!-- more --></div><br /><h2>Explaining the basics of programming in 15 minutes</h2>The solution to the first problem was to scratch TryRuby.org from the program. Not saying TryRuby.org isn't useful, but it's not ideal when you have a larger group of people trying to keep up with you. Instead, I advised girls to go through the exercises at home, and introduced some basic concepts of programming in a different way.<br /><br />I decided to show participants how to use <i>irb</i> (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interactive_Ruby_Shell">Interactive Ruby Shell</a>) in Terminal and how to create Ruby files in Sublime Text and running them from a Terminal (<i>ruby file.rb)</i>. In this way, I also addressed the second problem, as I gradually introduced the tools they would be using during the workshop. With different irb and .rb examples, I quickly introduced some of the most basic concepts of programming languages: different types of objects (strings, integers), methods, variables, if statements. Really basic stuff.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7T4GcLzOyrk/UTzwtRarA3I/AAAAAAAAAv4/RQujf3cOuqs/s1600/big-scary-dragon-lego.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-7T4GcLzOyrk/UTzwtRarA3I/AAAAAAAAAv4/RQujf3cOuqs/s1600/big-scary-dragon-lego.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />I also decided to introduce a new metaphor for computer programs:<b> a big, scary dragon</b>, which is what code looks like to beginners. It's only upon closer inspection that you realize that the dragon is built with basic Lego blocks you get to know right at the beginning of any coding course. When learning code for the first time, you can't go straight into building a big dragon, of course; it might even seem like an impossible task! So you start practicing by making small houses, cars, until you get a hang of it or find a good coach or online tutorial that shares with you the dragon construction secrets.<br /><br />I know, the explanation wasn't perfect, and maybe it wasn't all clear to those with zero experience. I hope I was at least able to show them programming can be deconstructed into smaller, readable and easy to understand blocks.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0A5Xxw8BlxI/UTzxDuPqYgI/AAAAAAAAAwA/wdt84LDOaFc/s1600/rails-mvc-sushi.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0A5Xxw8BlxI/UTzxDuPqYgI/AAAAAAAAAwA/wdt84LDOaFc/s1600/rails-mvc-sushi.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />And finally, I also added a slide about the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/codeinmotion/mvc-demystified-essence-of-ruby-on-rails">MVC architecture</a>&nbsp;that basically serves the purpose of explaining why there are so many different folders and files in a Rails project. I heard some coaches referring to the slide during their explanations, so I think it did its trick.<br /><br /><h2>Web and programming intro slides (English and Slovenian)</h2>I wrote in more detail about how I used the rest of the slides to explain the internet and web apps in <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html">my previous post</a>, so today I'm just going to share the updated slides again. The original lecture used Slovenian slides, but I also made an English translation. If you do find any of the stuff useful, do feel free to borrow.<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661527" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/the-web-and-programming-an-introduction-simple-short-and-friendly" target="_blank" title="The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly ">The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly </a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661515" style="border: 1px solid rgb(204, 204, 204); margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"></iframe></div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/uvod-v-internet-in-programiranje-enostavno-kratko-in-prijazno" target="_blank" title="Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno">Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><br />And finally, if you happen to understand Slovenian, you can also watch a recording of my lecture below. Even without speaking a word of Slovenian you'll probably appreciate the awesomeness of the video player used below, combining both video and slides. If that's the case, you should head over to <a href="http://www.viidea.com/">Viidea's website</a>&nbsp;right away to learn more about the awesome platform that makes this possible.<br /><br /><iframe frameborder="0" height="350" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="http://tsstartup.viidea.net/rg12_isakovic_uvod_v_internet/video/1/iframe/" width="100%"></iframe><br /><br />Disclosure: Viidea was yet again one of the sponsors of <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Rails Girls Ljubljana</a> and also recorded our lectures. They are super cool, so make sure to tell all your friends about their product!<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/how-lego-dragon-helped-me-explain.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons learned from Rails Girls and why we really do need more women in tech]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>It can be surprisingly easy to not notice things because "that's just the way it is". I have to admit I used to feel that way about the lack of women in tech. Just as a lot of women in the industry, I quickly started to think of myself as on of the guys and not even notice that I'm consistently a part of a minority at most tech events. In some ways, I was lucky that my mom was a geek even before that was a fashionable word and that I grew up without ever knowing computers were boys’ toys.&nbsp;But once you do start paying attention, it's impossible to turn the other way.</p><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/RailsGirlsLjubljana" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4OKqKxKxZV0/UTm6bGHM6UI/AAAAAAAAAvo/7GSUhnkdTfc/s1600/734397_517868904919059_991205745_n.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Self-driving cars will be on our roads soon, so why is it that seeing a large group of girls in front of a computer science faculty is still an exception reserved for Rails Girls events?&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table><br /><!-- more --><h2>Once you notice the gap, it stings your eyes</h2>I first started paying attention a few years ago. Ok, I'm one of the few women in tech. But surely things are changing because it's getting easier to get involved in the field? I mean, it's not like you've got to be super geeky to have a computer in 2013, programming languages have actually become readable to mere mortals, and you can learn how to code online. Yeah, all right, I see more girls popping up at events, but not nearly enough. Andraž Tori  recently did a great <a href="http://andraz.wpengine.com/2013/02/women-in-computer-science/" title="http://andraz.wpengine.com/2013/02/women-in-computer-science/">analysis of women in computer science at University in Ljubljana</a> and the data doesn't really show any positive trends.<br /><br />Which is all why I agreed to do lecture at MobileCamp Ljubljana almost exactly two years ago: <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2011/03/android-for-girls-new-frontier.html" title="/2011/03/android-for-girls-new-frontier.html">Android for girls: a new frontier</a>. I was quite self-conscious about speaking about about the topic. But you know what? It actually got a lot of positive attention! I realized that a lot of guys, developers, in fact don't usually think about half of their potential customers and they welcomed my practical tips on how to make apps more women (aka human) friendly! Crazy, right?<br /><br /><h2>Why is it even important to get more women in tech?</h2>After that experience it was easier for me to do a couple of more lectures on the topic of women in IT and especially startups. And while I was preparing the lectures (you can browse the slides below), I discovered more and more research pointing to the fact that this is a real issue in most parts of the world! <b>Women are increasingly more interested in technology, from the consumer side, but they are not as actively involved in the creation of technology. </b>Which of course means that we have tons of gadgets and apps on the market that were clearly made by white, straight guys living in a tech bubble. Nothing wrong by being a white, straight guy, mind you, but that's not even a majority group in the world. So how can we get all other groups to join the fun?<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15326515" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/what-about-the-other-half-of-your-customers" target="_blank" title="What about the other half of your customers?">What about the other half of your customers?</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15449092?startSlide=3" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="512"> </iframe> </div><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><div style="text-align: center;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/startup-women-startupday" target="_blank" title="Zakaj v startup svetu nikoli ni vrste pred ženskim straniščem?">Zakaj v startup svetu nikoli ni vrste pred ženskim straniščem?</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div></div><br /><h2>My suspicious were confirmed by reading applications for Rails Girls </h2>One thing I found I could do was to accept the challenge of organizing <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, a programming workshop for girls. Little did I know what I was getting myself into. The demand blew our mind. Surpassed even the wildest expectations. And by reading through each and every one of the 586 applications for our first workshop, I did get further proof that this was a real issue.<br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>Girls, women of all ages are eager to learn about how the tools we use every day are made.</strong> Telling us about how their boyfriends, fathers, other men in their lives, dismiss their interest in technology with "You wouldn't understand." or "You wouldn't find that interesting." Women of all ages saying they always felt like programming was only for guys. Women embracing the opportunity to learn a technical subject in a safe environment where guys can’t accuse them of asking stupid questions. And so on and on.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-783NUjYE_fQ/UTm3TzayW-I/AAAAAAAAAu4/EyiIe92b6dQ/s640/RailsGirlsLjubljana-racunalnik-KatarinaJazbec.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Photo by Katarina Jazbec</i></td></tr></tbody></table>I already wrote about what a <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html" title="/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html">magical event our first Rails Girls workshop was</a>. Not just because of the girls’ enthusiasm, but also because of our wonderful coaches. Guys and girls, experienced programmers, most without teaching experience. All eager to do it again.<br /><br /><h2>Rails Girls Ljubljana strikes again, this time with high school girls</h2>And we did it again. This time with the help of the <a href="http://www.fri.uni-lj.si/">Faculty of Computer in Information Science</a> here in Ljubljana. As we were discussing a joint workshop, we realized we could do a workshop just before high school students in our country decide where to continue their education. And so <b>we specifically tried to promote the workshop among high school girls.</b> This time we got 135 applications, though only 50 girls were under the age of 19 (I'm sure we’d get way more applications if we hadn't specified the event was mainly for high schoolers).<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.517860094919940.1073741825.466225130083437&type=3" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-r_e76USRVQg/UTm4GEmWdAI/AAAAAAAAAvE/q1aqbZm31MM/s1600/6553_517433124962637_241234575_n.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><br /></td></tr></tbody></table>We accepted all high school girls who applied. And on March 2 had another great event. It was a bit different though. Some girls were more shy, one even gave up after a mere hour - we had no such case at our first workshop, where the average age was well above 30. But some of the girls were even more eager than last time. <strong>Three interesting stories stood out for me</strong>:<br /><ul><li>A group of girls was interested in seeing the server room at the faculty.<br /></li><li>Another group was discussing about making an app for rating boys at their school. That’s, by the way, how Facebook started #justsaying<br /></li><li>A group told their coach they weren’t interested in the design tutorial. Instead, they wanted their coach to show them how to make another app, so that they would be able to do it on their own at home again.<br /></li></ul>So, you still want to tell me girls find programming and technology boring? All they need is a positive experience, and their imagination starts working at full speed! I was also pleasantly surprised when a TV crew visited our event, saying they got at least three emails&nbsp;internally&nbsp;saying they should stop by. And while we didn't make it into prime time news, we had a slot in the Saturday evening news on the national TV network. If you understand Slovenian or don't mind just looking at the action, you <a href="http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/porocila-ob-22h/ava2.160117678/00:06:31/0:8:20/">can see the news here</a>.<br /><br /><h2>Lessons learned from Rails Girls</h2>To sum it all up, here are some of the lessons I have learned while getting more actively involved in promoting technology among women:<br /><ul><li><b>We need more events like Rails Girls.</b> Seeing a room full of girls coding should be no more strange than a room full of guys coding.<br /></li><li>We still need to figure out a follow up to Rails Girls. Advanced workshops, meetups, hackatons… I don't know yet. But it needs to become a regular thing, not just an occasional flash mob.<br /></li><li>Yes, you can learn to code online in many different ways. But it's still intimidating for a lot of beginners, especially women who still think technology isn't for them. The social aspect of learning and the ability to have a coach tailor the learning experience on the spot is very important for some! <br /></li><li>Related to the previous point, a relaxed and flexible environment facilitates learning. Small groups working at their own pace, coming up with new questions as they go. All girls did learn a lot at our workshops, but they didn’t necessarily all learn the same exact things.<br /></li><li>I really enjoyed working with the faculty on our second workshop. Their coaches had no problem embracing the Rails Girls organized chaos, and they also worked well with other coaches. And I think this can be a good model of academia and the private sector joining forces. It was great seeing coaches with different background sharing their knowledge and experiences with beginners. I'd like to see that happen more regularly, and not just with coding for women.</li></ul><div><br /></div><h2>Encourage women in your life to embrace technology </h2>And by the way, it is not a coincidence that I am writing this blog post on March 8, the International Women's Day. It's a day when my Facebook feed is filled with pictures of flower bouquets and kind words of appreciation. Thanks for noticing us for one day, but you know what? <strong>If we really want to help women succeed, we need to arm them with two key things: education and technology.</strong><br /><br />ICT is continuously transforming all areas of our lives, and we can't allow half of the population to fall behind, to stay on the spectator side. Girls, women, it's time to stand up, speak up, and embrace technology! Just because you have a womb, it doesn't mean you can't handle a computer. The <a href="http://blog.fogcreek.com/girls-go-geek-again/">first software programmers were women</a>, let's not forget that! And it's not about talking over the world, it's about equal opportunities and active participation in the shaping of a better future for all of us.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://blog.fogcreek.com/girls-go-geek-again/" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CozWAob3BNM/UTm5iuTrQiI/AAAAAAAAAvY/1uftGYgX2GQ/s400/eniac+girls.jpg" width="580" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Eniac Girls started it ...&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table>Don't get me wrong, I don't want everyone becoming a programmer - I am not a programmer myself, yet I benefit immensely in everything I do by understanding how things work. There are a lot of cool things you can do with technology and soon we will have very few jobs that don't involve any digital skills. Will you be ready for that world?<br /><br />To finish on a positive note, I would like to point out that there are many wonderful initiatives around the world you can get involved in. <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a>, <a href="http://girlgeekdinners.com/">Geek Girl Dinners</a>, <a href="http://www.ladygeek.com/" title="http://www.ladygeek.com">Lady Geek</a>, <a href="http://sheplusplus.stanford.edu/" title="http://sheplusplus.stanford.edu">She++</a>, just to mention a few. And in Europe we have a big partnership, <a href="http://women2020.org/" title="http://women2020.org">Women2020</a>, launching today at <a href="http://www.digitaleurope.org/" title="http://www.digitaleurope.org/">DIGITALEUROPE</a>, <i>"whose mission is to promote women’s contribution to achieving the Europe 2020 vision of smart, sustainable and inclusive growth."</i> There will be many big scale events and discussions going on throughout the year, culminating in the release of Women2020 Action Plan in December.<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://women2020.org/" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="56" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1aET6FgYwEc/UTm4uj_gMiI/AAAAAAAAAvM/R_kT5XvMVko/s400/cropped-women202011.jpg" width="400" /></a></div><br />Having just met many wonderful and enthusiastic women both from the European Comission and various big and small enterprises in <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2013/03/how-i-found-great-chocolate-in-brussels.html">Brussels</a>, I think this could be a big and important thing. But in the end, it will come to each and every one of us, women and men, to play our part and provide support for women entering the field. I certainly hope I will have a lot more to write about the subject this year. And not just about the issue, but mostly about the results of our efforts.<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2013/03/lessons-learned-from-rails-girls-and.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When magic happens at Rails Girls Ljubljana]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
What happens when you fill 2 classrooms and 1 big conference room at <a href="http://en.telekom.si/">Telekom Slovenije</a> with over 70 girls of all ages, who want to build their own web app, and 30 coaches, experienced web developers? No, it's not a rhetorical question, it's a real challenge!<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-vkCHcmWd2Bg/UM72ZDyLCyI/AAAAAAAAAos/mo_g7PzdImg/s1600/219146_482121458493804_716264997_o.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="393" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-vkCHcmWd2Bg/UM72ZDyLCyI/AAAAAAAAAos/mo_g7PzdImg/s400/219146_482121458493804_716264997_o.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Over a hundred people at the first Rails Girls Ljubljana workshop! Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Sure, the girls are among the most enthusiastic out of the <a href="http://visual.ly/rails-girls-ljubljana-december-2012-english-version">586 that signed</a>&nbsp;up for <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Rails Girls Ljubljana</a>, a free two-day workshop. But most of them have no experience with programming whatsoever. And the coaches sure are all excited to help and hope to see more girls among their ranks, yet most of them have little or no experience with teaching, especially with teaching complete beginners. Even after more than a month of intensive planning, countless emails and meetings, I, as the main organizer, can't help but feel nervous on Friday, December 14, the first day of the first ever Rails Girls Ljubljana. Is anyone even going to show up?<br /><!-- more --><br />The doubts and worries dissipate once I see all those smiling faces. Once I see the coaches interacting with the girls. Patiently answering all questions, making sure <a href="http://guides.railsgirls.com/install/">everything is installed</a> successfully and ready to go for the workshop. You can feel the excitement and positive energy in the air!<br /><blockquote class="twitter-tweet">3,2,1... in gremooooo, punce! <a href="http://t.co/zIPk6WPi" title="http://twitter.com/RailsGirls_LJ/status/279636337550843905/photo/1">twitter.com/RailsGirls_LJ/…</a><br />— RailsGirls Ljubljana (@RailsGirls_LJ) <a data-datetime="2012-12-14T17:17:53+00:00" href="https://twitter.com/RailsGirls_LJ/status/279636337550843905">December 14, 2012</a></blockquote><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="http://blog.ialja.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"></script><br />The next day, Saturday, December 15, I wake up an hour before the alarm goes off. My mind keeps running through the to-dos, making last minute plans. The nervousness has already been replaced by excitement. Fueled by the positive energy of the day before, I can't wait to welcome the participants in the morning. A lot of them arrive early, also eager to start and get the first dose of coffee.<br /><br />After breakfast we start by welcoming everybody, but I try to keep the intro short. I can't wait to hear our motivational talks by two great girl geeks. <a href="https://twitter.com/sparkica">Mateja</a> tells them about how programming will probably make them feel like Alice in Wonderland, but also highlights the thrill of programming, the joy of <i>creating</i> something on your own out of code. Dunja then takes over to remind us of the rich history of women in programming. <br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bEur79eYw4o/UM74edH3lDI/AAAAAAAAAo8/g2og-6GANgY/s1600/316607_482120485160568_1640987580_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="393" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bEur79eYw4o/UM74edH3lDI/AAAAAAAAAo8/g2og-6GANgY/s400/316607_482120485160568_1640987580_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Hana making sure our motivational talks get recorded!&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Both talks make a great introduction to the practical part of the day. I first explain how the internet works and what we'll be doing during the workshop using <a href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html">Octocat, sushi and sushi chefs</a>. The smiles on the girls' faces are a good sign, although I also see some traces of doubts "Will I really be able to do that?".<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-zmXneBGpD14/UM73Ycmo3rI/AAAAAAAAAo0/Njx-IX_4akI/s1600/68657_482120785160538_711443265_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="399" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-zmXneBGpD14/UM73Ycmo3rI/AAAAAAAAAo0/Njx-IX_4akI/s400/68657_482120785160538_711443265_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Explaining objects and methods with a lot of waving around :) Photo by: <a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a>&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table>We play with <a href="http://tryruby.org/">TryRuby.org</a> a bit and then learn how to Google everything with the <a href="http://blog.railsgirls.com/post/20405930015/bentobox-learn-the-language-of-technology">Bento Box exercise</a>. But that's just about enough theory, the girls want to get their own hands dirty with code! Without further ado, they form small groups of maximum three participants and start creating their <a href="http://guides.railsgirls.com/app/">idea app</a> with the help of their coach.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lPQz8L9YktE/UM74fCAYqDI/AAAAAAAAApA/CgIrPcxv_QQ/s1600/380677_482120988493851_1888856434_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="386" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lPQz8L9YktE/UM74fCAYqDI/AAAAAAAAApA/CgIrPcxv_QQ/s400/380677_482120988493851_1888856434_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Making sense of the technical mambo jumbo during the Bento Box exercise.&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>And that, ladies and gentlemen, is when the magic happens! There is no other way to describe it. I walk around and all the girls have their Terminal windows open and are building their first app. The coaches are also in the zone, explaining everything, even drawing some of the most abstract concepts on whiteboards.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HLHiffWKyQI/UM74hLRIoPI/AAAAAAAAApY/DZRp_9Bfd18/s1600/60892_482121105160506_1144614278_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="393" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HLHiffWKyQI/UM74hLRIoPI/AAAAAAAAApY/DZRp_9Bfd18/s400/60892_482121105160506_1144614278_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>One of the rooms, full of girls and coaches.&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>We have a hard time making everyone wrap up for lunch. I hear girls and coaches talking abut their apps while waiting in line. The girls seem especially eager to finish fast and get back to their code!<br /><br />Food obviously makes us all a bit sleepy, so we guide everyone outside for a good dose of fresh air, a quick stretch and we finally do our <a href="http://fridayhug.com/">#FridayHug</a> group shot. There are so many of us we hardly fit into a single frame!<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-FEIEhhwjspU/UM79gyXUDHI/AAAAAAAAAp4/YB-BSwnERss/s1600/8848_482121291827154_160897704_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="393" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-FEIEhhwjspU/UM79gyXUDHI/AAAAAAAAAp4/YB-BSwnERss/s640/8848_482121291827154_160897704_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Building a wep app.&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>After the group shot the girls return straight to their laptops and continue working on their apps. It doesn't take long for some groups to reach the "What's Next?" part of the guide. Before the workshop is over, some have already added comments, ratings, deployed their app online with Heroku, some are playing with CSS or working on special assignments their coaches gave them. By 6 PM everyone has their own web app. We are all tired, but happy and excited. The girls, the coaches are all thanking me for a great experience as asking me: "When are we going to do this again?"<br /><br />"After I get some sleep," I smile. There is no other choice. <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">Rails Girls</a> will happen again in Ljubljana, probably in other cities in Slovenia as well. Girls want to code, coaches (boys and girls!) are eager to help them out. We still don't know exactly how and when, but we have to do this again. For all those girls (over 500 of them) who couldn't be with us this time, for all those girls who haven't even heard of us yet or maybe who didn't dare to fill in the signup form. We will be back.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PZlbI9WgUgw/UM74fg9mh2I/AAAAAAAAApI/nMkXI1LuevE/s1600/532527_482121845160432_2111096409_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="393" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-PZlbI9WgUgw/UM74fg9mh2I/AAAAAAAAApI/nMkXI1LuevE/s400/532527_482121845160432_2111096409_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Happy Rails Girls and coaches!&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a>&nbsp;</i></td></tr></tbody></table>And we're also hoping to keep in touch with the 1st generation of Rails Girls and coaches. We already have a support group on Facebook running, maybe we'll even organize regular informal meetups to check everyone's progress.<br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iEqZN2ZM4uk/UM74hzoMMZI/AAAAAAAAApk/TOTLuLyzKFw/s1600/74069_482121261827157_1147127405_n.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="386" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iEqZN2ZM4uk/UM74hzoMMZI/AAAAAAAAApk/TOTLuLyzKFw/s400/74069_482121261827157_1147127405_n.jpg" width="590" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i>Lots of love and positive energy!&nbsp;Photo by:&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina Jazbec</a></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Finally, I would like to thank everyone who made this event such a magic experience. <a href="http://www.alesspetic.si/">Aleš</a>, our digital champion and the leading force of <a href="http://www.tsstartup.si/">TSstartup</a> accelerator (where I currently work as a community manager), for offering me the challenge of organizing the event and supporting us along the way. <a href="https://twitter.com/alivea">Živa</a> for all your support and the super awesome <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> t-shirt, <a href="https://twitter.com/AjdaAzman">Ajda</a> for all your energy and help, <a href="https://twitter.com/tadejab">Tadeja</a> for the great texts and tweets, <a href="https://twitter.com/RokPiletic">Rok</a> for surprising us with handmade heart-shaped desserts, <a href="https://twitter.com/anjalazar">Anja</a> for hosting two thirds of the Croatian team. Telekom for providing all the little details needed for such an event, all our other sponsors and partners.&nbsp;All of our coaches, especially <a href="https://twitter.com/nursahketene">Nur</a>, who flew in from Finland just for the weekend to be with us, <a href="https://twitter.com/GregovLucija">Lucija</a> (the cats say hello!), <a href="https://twitter.com/ivanavasilj">Ivana</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/mislav">Mislav</a> from <a href="http://railsgirls.com/zagreb">Rails Girls Zagreb</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/goranche">Goran</a> for simultaneously lecturing in the other classroom with me, DJ-ing at the after party at TSstartup and providing tons of support, and all the other coaches for being so patient and willing to get a sore throat from answering every single question the girls had. Mateja and Dunja for doing their talk twice in both our classrooms and for motivating the girls.&nbsp;Hana from&nbsp;<a href="http://www.viidea.com/">Viidea</a>&nbsp;who filmed the lectures,&nbsp;<a href="http://otrokvesolja.blogspot.com/">Katarina</a>&nbsp;for great event photos (you can see&nbsp;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/RailsGirlsLjubljana/photos_stream">more on our Facebook page</a>). All the participants for your braveness, persistence and curiosity. <a href="https://twitter.com/lindaliukas">Linda</a> for sending us a lovely greeting video (unfortunately we couldn't play it due to audio problems) and for starting Rails Girls in the first place. Even though I wasn't a participant at the workshop, I learned a lot in the past month or so. I got to know GitHub and met so many great people along the way. Thank you all, and I hope to see you next time!<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/when-magic-happens-at-rails-girls.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Explaining the web and web programming with Octocat, sushi and fish]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html"/>
    <updated>2012-12-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>One of challenges of organizing <a href="http://railsgirls.com/ljubljana">Rails Girls Ljubljana</a> was coming up with short lectures that would prepare the girls, absolute beginners, to understand the basic terminology of the web and what they would be working on.</p>Sure, there are some existing presentations online about what programming is and where Rails fits in the whole story, but I thought beginners could benefit from something a bit more simple, funny and thus memorable. Which is why I borrowed <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a>'s mascot <a href="http://octodex.github.com/">Octocat</a> and sent him off on a journey to find sushi without fish on the web. Wait, what?<br /><!-- more --><br />Have a look for yourself, here are the slides, both in English and Slovenian (the original I used for my lecture):<br /><br /><iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="mozallowfullscreen" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661527" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="webkitallowfullscreen" width="512"> </iframe> <br /><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/the-web-and-programming-an-introduction-simple-short-and-friendly" target="_blank" title="The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly ">The web and programming: an introduction - Simple, short and friendly </a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div><br /><iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0" height="421" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" mozallowfullscreen="mozallowfullscreen" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/15661515" style="border-width: 1px 1px 0; border: 1px solid #CCC; margin-bottom: 5px;" webkitallowfullscreen="webkitallowfullscreen" width="512"> </iframe> <br /><div style="margin-bottom: 5px;"><strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/uvod-v-internet-in-programiranje-enostavno-kratko-in-prijazno" target="_blank" title="Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno">Uvod v internet in programiranje: Enostavno, kratko in prijazno</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a></strong> </div><br />In case you find the slides useful, the main tip for presenting with them is: don't explain everything on the slides, focus on the story. In the first part, where I introduce the client-server model of the web, I didn't explain the technical terms too much. I compared IP addresses to phone numbers servers have and DNS servers to a phonebook. I do think it's good for beginners to be eposed to these terms, but they don't really need to know in detail what they mean.<br /><br />When talking about GET requests, I didn't explain HTTP or the format of a request. A GET request is all they need to hear, and you can mention that sometimes the server doesn't find what you're looking for in which case you get and <a href="http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/60-really-cool-and-creative-error-404-pages/">Error 404 page</a>. But if the server does find the web page, it sends it in HTML to your browser. Knowing all the steps will make it easier for people tounderstand that there are many steps involved into the process and that fast loading pages can only happen if all part of the process work as they are supposed to.<br /><br />In the second part I explained the different between a static and a dynamic web page using Octocat, who doesn't quite want the usual sushi. I explained the concept of a web app with the sushi chef living on the server, ready to tailor the content (or looks) of the web pages to each user's needs and interests, just like Facebook. And once you have a sushi chef, it's easy to explain Ruby as the language you need to learn to make the chef (the web app) do what you want.<br /><br />Simple, short, friendly and apparently memorable: one of the participants was just asking me about Octocat and sushi on Twitter, so I guess a different approach did the trick!<br /><br /><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-8DX0ZyAnn0Q/UM4u0gg6VII/AAAAAAAAAoU/fp7QnqPoDow/s1600/rails-girls-intro-web.png" /></a></div><br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2012/12/explaining-web-and-web-programming-with.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 key mobile trends you should know about [Lecture]]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ialja.com/2011/07/5-key-mobile-trends-you-should-know.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ialja.com/2011/07/5-key-mobile-trends-you-should-know</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Recently I was invited to prepare a guest lecture for a small group of business and management students attending an E-learning course as part of their Summer School in Koper. I was told to choose a topic that would be fresh, something that students don't get to hear about that often in regular classes.<br /><p>And that's why I decided to put together an <b>overview of some of the key trends in the mobile industry</b> that are already influencing the way we study, work and socialize, and will probably be an increasingly important part of our day to day life. You can find the slides and the video of my lecture, as well as a text recap, in this post.</p><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-2aUbDxvFBiA/ThYi-IEQddI/AAAAAAAAAG4/JeD6QsZPcPQ/s1600/mobile_trends_lecture-ialja.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-2aUbDxvFBiA/ThYi-IEQddI/AAAAAAAAAG4/JeD6QsZPcPQ/s1600/mobile_trends_lecture-ialja.jpg" /></a></div><a name='more'></a><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Lecture slides with additional resources</span></span></b><br /><br />Because choosing just a few trends, just a few technologies wasn't easy, I decided to prepare slides that students could also use to explore parts of the lecture they found most interesting in more details. That is why I added a lot of links to current articles with cases studies, stats, analysis and what not. You can view all of the slides embedded below.<br /><div id="__ss_8505250" style="width: 510px;"><strong style="display: block; margin: 12px 0 4px;"><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja/5-key-mobile-trends-youshould-know-about" target="_blank" title="5 key mobile trends you should know about">5 key mobile trends you&nbsp;should know about</a></strong> <iframe frameborder="0" height="426" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/8505250" width="510"></iframe> <br /><div style="padding: 5px 0 12px;">View more <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/" target="_blank">presentations</a> from <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/ialja" target="_blank">Alja Isakovic</a> </div></div><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;">Don't like flipping through slides? Here's a recap.</span></span></b><br /><br />To sum it all up in a more coherent form, here are the 5 key mobile trends I decided to highlight:<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #3d85c6;">1. Mobile devices are making learning (and other activities) more magical</span></b><br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-rdamdLBTkgI/ThYe6jYoreI/AAAAAAAAAGk/uKosOTlfIS0/s1600/magic_touch_apple.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-rdamdLBTkgI/ThYe6jYoreI/AAAAAAAAAGk/uKosOTlfIS0/s1600/magic_touch_apple.jpg" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">The magic of touch (source: </span></span></i><a href="http://www.apple.com/education/"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Apple</span></span></i></a><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">)</span></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Interactive content is nothing new. What is new is the way mobile devices such as smartphones and tablets (that include smart sensors and touch screens) allow us to physically touch the content. It does feel a bit like magic, touching just isn't the same as clicking with a mouse. It's more intuitive, more personal. It gets to you.<br /><br />And while today apps like <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U-edAGLokak">Our Choice</a> are often seen as fun gimmicks that you can use to impress an audience, I believe that in a few years we'll wonder how we've ever settled for learning with content we couldn't touch directly. Ok, make that a couple of more years; we all know most edu folks aren't exactly early adopters. But I believe that someday the shift will happen, because touch just feels so natural to all of us. <br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #3d85c6;">2. Apps and app stores are rocking the world</span></b><br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-OrnOm-kUMp8/TXJ1CCZiP3I/AAAAAAAAAs8/qbLafMHHrDE/s1600/iPad-apps.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-OrnOm-kUMp8/TXJ1CCZiP3I/AAAAAAAAAs8/qbLafMHHrDE/s1600/iPad-apps.jpg" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">The App Store has over 400,000 apps (source: </span></span></i><a href="http://www.apple.com/ipad/from-the-app-store/"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Apple</span></span></i></a><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">)</span></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>There certainly is an app and an app store for that - whatever your "that" might be. Apart from satisfying our desire to help <a href="http://www.rovio.com/index.php?page=angry-birds">angry birds</a> get revenge on those naughty, egg-stealing pigs, mobile apps (and the development ecosystem Apple envisioned) are teaching everyone some important lessons. There are many reasons why apps are so successful. The most obvious one is because they are just so much more awesome and magical, if you will, than our desktop software.<br /><br />But another very important lesson (one that Apple already learned with the iTunes Store) is that we don't mind paying for digital content if it's easy and convenient to do so and if the content provides us with enough value. And, on the other side of the fence, we are eager to develop good content  if we get the chance to earn a few bucks and be the coolest kid in town aka the app store of our choice.<br /><br />The application stores are also making business models that rely on selling virtual content (in-app purchases) more popular and widely acceptable. I don't think I'm stretching it too far if I predict that in a few year we'll be spending 99 cents on fancy templates for Microsoft Office. Right within the software, or app, as we'll all be calling it by then. One click, ka-ching! Of course, Apple will probably the first one to offer in-app purchases in Pages ;) Which all leads us to the next trend...<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #3d85c6;">3. Website and desktops are changing because of mobile devices</span></b><br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-RRirp1lvPqg/ThYf5Xo0HkI/AAAAAAAAAGo/eTX6G3Z5d2U/s1600/mac_lion_launchpad.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-RRirp1lvPqg/ThYf5Xo0HkI/AAAAAAAAAGo/eTX6G3Z5d2U/s1600/mac_lion_launchpad.jpg" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;">Apps in Mac OS X - looks familiar, doesn't it? (source: </span></span></i><a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/whats-new/"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;">Apple</span></span></i></a><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;">)</span></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table><a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/whats-new/">Mac OS X Lion</a>, which will hopefully be released in a week or so, looks like iPad's big brother. Full screen apps, a new app launcher, the Mac App Store, heavily integrated gestures... Yep, Apple has learned a lot from iOS, their mobile operating system, and it's bringing most&nbsp;of it&nbsp;(including the App Store business models) to their big, desktop OS.<br /><br />And don't think this is just an Apple fad - <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p92QfWOw88I">Windows 8</a> will also look like Windows Phone 7's big brother. It seem like we've got no choice but to adapt to seeing our desktops becoming some sort of clumsier mobile device with a big screen.<br /><br />Not to mention websites also all want to look like apps. And <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/">HTML5</a>, CSS3 &amp; co. will make that all possible. Expect to see more websites that look and behave like apps or at least websites that will be smart enough to have the decency to self adjust to your screen size and even device type. I sure do hope to see more responsive design on the web in the coming years.<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #3d85c6;">4. Location data makes mobile better</span></b><br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XxO-4voEnyM/ThYgU-9v5QI/AAAAAAAAAGs/kAvuIEs3yeg/s1600/FB-places.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XxO-4voEnyM/ThYgU-9v5QI/AAAAAAAAAGs/kAvuIEs3yeg/s1600/FB-places.jpg" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Even Facebook is crazy about Places (source: </span></span></i><a href="https://www.facebook.com/places"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Facebook</span></span></i></a><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">)</span></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>Ugh, location. Where to start? It's pretty clear that adding location data can make many services more useful and even fun. From local searches that help you discover cool nearby places, to the phenomena of telling all your friends not just what you're doing, but also <i>where</i> you're doing it and getting specials or offers in return, mobile payments and mobile commerce taking off, geo-fences that enable location reminds, ad-hoc social networks based on location, and... and... and...<br /><br />There is A LOT going on, so I really suggest you take a look at some of those additional links provided in the slide deck above. There's no doubt that relying on location data to enhance services is a big trend that is just starting to evolve. As a side note, it is of course also worth noting that we have a lot of open questions about privacy and trust to figure out yet, especially when it comes to sensitive location data.<br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #3d85c6;">5. The cloud will make everything easier</span></b><br /><br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-b4_znBBN3MM/ThYg3oEaQdI/AAAAAAAAAGw/OQle_j38uog/s1600/cloud.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-b4_znBBN3MM/ThYg3oEaQdI/AAAAAAAAAGw/OQle_j38uog/s1600/cloud.jpg" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Don't worry, the cloud will take care of everything (source: </span></span></i><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing"><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">Wikipedia</span></span></i></a><i><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: x-small;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #666666;">)</span></span></i></td></tr></tbody></table>As more and more companies expect us to have more and more of their devices of different sizes and shapes, it's a bit of a relief that they are also thinking about ways of connecting all our devices and making up for our instinctive human laziness when it comes to backing up and syncing. The new wave of cloud services from all the big boys are all trying to making it easy for us to access our content, data and files from any of the devices we own.<br /><br />And while most people, who today know very well computers just aren't to be trusted, are still skeptical of all these promises (it does look a bit like science fiction, doesn't it?), I think in a few years we'll all get adjusted to things just working seamlessly through the cloud. <br /><br />And that is probably the master trend to rule them all - the technology is slowly getting out of the way, fading in the background, while allowing us to be the forgetful, spontaneous, touch fixated human beings that we all are. In this world, experience is the killer app. <br /><br /><b><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;"><span class="Apple-style-span" style="color: #e69138;">Prefer video to text? No problem, look over here!</span></span></b><br /><br />If you prefer to listen to me go through these key points and watch me passionately gesticulate as an added bonus, you can also take a look at the video recording from the lecture (I do apologize for a few minor technical glitches; an hour long HD video is apparently quite a big bite for my good old iMac to swallow).<br /><br /><div style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="349" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/qYfbE8hKVec" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></div><div style="text-align: center;"><br /></div>As always, you are more than welcome to leave your comments, questions, likes, tweets, +1's and what not. All feedback is appreciated!<br/><br/><hr/><br/><italic>Originally published at <a href='http://ialja.blogspot.com/2011/07/5-key-mobile-trends-you-should-know.html'>http://ialja.blogspot.com/2011/07/5-key-mobile-trends-you-should-know.html</a></italic><br/><br/></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
